So today, we're going to talk about evaluation.
So far in this class we've done everything we
need to train a language model.
We defined the architecture, the optimizer, the main training
loop.
We showed how to make the training fast with kernels,
parallelism.
And then we saw scaling laws.
We saw a little bit of how to make inference fast as well.
So the only missing piece now is talking about the data
that you train on.
So we're going to spend next week talking about that.
And data is going to shape the model behavior.
If you train on code, then presumably
your model is going to be good at code.
If you train only on DNA sequences,
it probably can't speak English.
But before we even get to data, we
need to talk about what behavior we want from a model,
and that's going to be the topic of evaluation.
So evaluation asks a very simple question--
given the model that we've trained, how good is it?
So what is good?
So evaluation might seem like a fairly mechanical process.
You define some prompts, you send
these prompts to your model, you get back some responses,
and then you compute the accuracy.
So why do we have a whole lecture on evaluation?
But actually, evaluation is a very deep topic,
and it's also very important because evaluation is what
shapes the development of AI.
Evaluation sets North Stars and model developers--
open, closed-- everyone looks at evaluation
as a measure of progress.
So by thinking carefully about your evaluation,
you implicitly shape the development
of what your model is going to be able to do.
So what's hard about evaluation is the following.
So often, you start it with an abstract construct of what
do I want my model to do?
Maybe I want my model to be good at conversation
or good at reasoning.
OK.
So those are abstract concepts.
And then evaluation is really the process
of turning that into a concrete metric powered by, presumably,
some concrete prompts or environments.
So this is going to be the core challenge,
and we'll see many examples of how
this process of abstract construct, concrete metric
shows up.
So let's go back to a question of what makes a model good.
Just kind of superficially.
Maybe a model is good if it does well on benchmarks.
So there's this website, Artificial Analysis,
which has become a bit of a standard for thinking about
quote unquote, "intelligence of models."
So if you go to Artificial Analysis AI,
you can see a ranking of different models from GPT-5.5,
all the way down-- well, there's many more models after this
point.
And so this is a measure.
It includes a bunch of different data sets, some of which
we'll talk about.
Or maybe a model is good if it does well on benchmark
and is also cheap to run, because cost should matter.
And this plot shows both the intelligence index
from before, but against how much money
it costs to run a particular model based on inference cost.
And you can see, of course, as you might expect,
that the two are correlated.
The more you pay to run, the higher the intelligence index,
but it's not exactly aligned.
But maybe a model is good if people just prefer it.
Later we'll also go a little bit more into depth.
So this is the take that Arena AI, formerly known
as Chatbot Arena, takes.
And you can form a ranking based on models,
based on whether people like it or not.
Or maybe a model is good if people simply
choose to use it, and therefore, pay for it.
So OpenRouter is this service that
allows one to use multiple different models
through a central endpoint.
And as a result, they collect a lot
of statistics of what models people are using.
And they publish statistics, which
is really interesting to look at,
the top bottles that are used through OpenRouter.
So now, this is not representative of all model
usage, but it gives you a sense of what people on open router
are doing.
And so this is kind of more of an economic lens.
I don't what good is, but if people are paying for it,
it must be good.
OK.
So none of those are necessarily the correct answer.
I don't know If there is a correct answer,
but I'm just trying to get you to think about different ways
of thinking about what good is.
So let's start now by looking at different ways, concrete ways,
of evaluating language models.
And there's no better place to start than going back
to the core idea of a language model, which
is that it's a distribution P of x over sequences of tokens.
And through that lens, there's a very natural way
to evaluate a distribution, which
is a perplexity, or likelihood or log loss.
Those are all kind of related concepts.
And it basically says, I have a test data set d,
and I'm going to see how much probability mass my language
model assigns to that d.
And I normalize it and divide so that the numbers
are more interpretable.
But that's basically it.
How much mass does my probability language model
assigned to a data set.
OK, so this is fairly natural.
In fact, when we were doing training,
we minimized the perplexity on the training set.
So the obvious thing to do is measure the perplexity
on the test set, and this is what people traditionally did
in language modeling research for many years throughout
the 2010s.
If you pick up a language modeling paper,
this is what they did.
And back then, standard data sets
included the Penn Treebank, WikiText-103.
There was also this One Billion Word Benchmark,
which was taken from machine translation sources.
And this is all in the classic paradigm, which is
in-distribution of evaluation.
You train on some train split of that data set,
and then you evaluate on some test split of that data set.
And people actually made a lot of progress,
which was just measured in perplexity reduction.
So for example, there's this famous paper
from 2016, which showed that you could
apply CNNs and LSTMs to this One Billion Word Benchmark
and get a huge perplexity reduction.
And bear in mind, around that time,
people were talking still about n-gram models and maybe
hybrid models.
And this was the first definitive result
that showed just pure neural is clearly the way to go.
OK, so life was very simple back then.
You train on the train split.
You test on a test split for perplexity.
So then when GPT-2 came around in 2019 from OpenAI,
they trained on the data set called
WebText, which was 40 gigabytes of text websites
that were linked from Reddit.
And the way they evaluated was actually different.
They evaluated zero-shot on standard data sets
that everyone else was evaluating on.
So this is out-of-distribution evaluation.
So this is a table from their paper, which show that as they
train different models.
So the biggest model is 1.5 billion parameters.
And they were able to show quite a bit of improvement,
especially on the small data sets.
So for example, PTB, which is a tiny data set.
They were getting 35 perplexity compared to the State
of The Art, which is 46.
Now, if you have enough in-distribution data,
you don't quite do as well as the SOTA.
But nonetheless, this is kind of impressive,
given that this model was not trained on One Billion Word's
data set at all.
I don't know.
Maybe there was some overlap, because I
don't know if they did a careful train test decontam.
And so it ushered in a new paradigm
of thinking about language models as not just
the in-distribution setting, but how
we wanted to train on a large data set
and evaluate on standard benchmarks, which nowadays I
think has been very common standard.
But back then, it was seen as a bit of a novelty.
I will also argue, since we're talking about perplexity, that
perplexity is you all need.
I wouldn't to take this too seriously,
but I think it is a mindset, I think,
that drives a lot of language modeling research.
And the basic argument goes like this.
So there's some true distribution out there--
let's call it t--
and you're training this model p.
So what is the best perplexity you could obtain?
Well, the best perplexity is the entropy
of that true distribution, and that
is realized when p equals t.
So by minimizing perplexity, you're basically
pushing down the perplexity.
And the only unique minimizer is when you actually
get the true distribution.
And when you have the true distribution, you're done.
You just model everything.
You can solve all the problems, and you
can do things like condition on the problem,
generate a solution.
You can condition on a question, generate the answer.
So by pushing down on perplexity,
we'll eventually reach AGI, is the argument.
I mean, this might sound, I don't know,
either a bit fantastical.
But in some sense, this is really,
I think, a strong driver of many people
who have been scaling and scaling language models
at a time when, maybe, the gains weren't as obvious.
Before GPT-3, I think it wasn't clear
that language models were going to have such a huge impact.
And it was really this belief that, if you drove perplexity
down, good things will happen.
So of course, Perplexity is maybe not all.
And one way to frame it is that perplexity is maybe more
than you need.
So for example, if you have a sentence like "Stanford was
founded in 1885," perplexity will say,
penalize the prediction on all tokens.
So in particular, it'll say, what is the probability of 1885,
given the rest?
And that token is probably pretty useful.
It's basically a Q&A example, phrased as sentence completion.
So it captures knowledge about the world.
But other ones-- for example, the first word of a sentence,
or even "founded"--
maybe not that interesting, I think.
And perplexity doesn't care.
It's going to charge you bits for every bit of a deviation
from the true distribution.
So there is a bit of a solution here,
which is you can always measure the conditional perplexity.
You can condition on some prompt,
and then you can measure the perplexity of the remaining
response.
So that allows you to, in general,
focus on certain tokens that you believe
to be relevant and less on others
that are sort of incidental.
OK.
And also, it's important to remember
that some benchmarks, even though they are not explicitly
a perplexity measure, are actually
just perplexity in disguise.
So, for example, if you think about closed tasks.
There's this lambada paper from, actually, a while ago,
2016, which is basically fill in the blank.
And you have a context, you have a sentence.
"Do you honestly think I will want you to have a blank."
And the goal is to figure out that word.
And even though this is measured in terms of accuracy,
it is really a next-token prediction problem.
And here, it's not perplexity of all the words,
it's carefully chosen.
If you read this paper, it's really carefully chosen
to be words, such that you actually need
a bunch of long-contexts to resolve.
So this is actually something that the early GPT papers really
latched on to because they were interested in long-context
modeling, thinking that that was a key to unlocking
reasoning and all these things.
And really, by focusing on positions
where, to resolve that, it requires
long-distance dependencies, is a way
to sharpen the perplexity to some phenomenon
that you care about.
Here's another popular classic data
set that you see in some language modeling vowels.
HellaSwag.
So what is HellaSwag?
They went to various different data sets and sources,
and came up with-- it's multiple choice,
but it's really sentence completion.
And at some level, it's perplexity.
So here's a sentence.
"A woman is outside with a bucket and a dog.
The dog is running around.
She blank."
And then you're trying to fill in which
sentence completes it the best.
So it's not exactly perplexity, it's multiple choice.
But in some ways, it's perplexity.
So one word of warning.
If you ever decide that you're sold on perplexity
as, really, the measure and you're
going to launch a leaderboard and have people compete
against perplexity, just a word of caution
is that, what is a perplexity leaderboard look like?
So people are going to submit a language model to you,
and you have to compute a logprob.
You send them the test data, and they give you back a logprob.
Well, you look at that and say, hmm,
that might be a little bit fishy because you
need to trust that the probabilities they hand back
to you are valid and that they sum to 1.
Otherwise, I could just have implement LM,
and it always returns 1 or, I guess, logprob 0.
And I would get very good perplexity,
but clearly, that's not a valid distribution.
And so with this contract it's not
really easy to check that someone is actually
internally having a log probability,
so there's some trust.
Maybe you have to look at the code or something.
For downstream tasks, this is much more straightforward
because you can have a black box LM.
I give you a prompt, you give me a response,
and I can just use that response and calculate some accuracy.
So perplexity is fundamentally different
because it deals with distributions,
and you have to be a bit careful.
And not to mention, there's lots of problems
with autoregressive models.
But if you have VAEs or there's some models where you can't even
compute the distribution-- you can compute only a bound--
then you have to really actually trust the math as well that this
is actually a valid bound.
OK.
So The summary of perplexity is that it is actually
still used quite heavily in language model development.
It has some nice properties.
We saw that it's generally used for scaling laws
because it's also smoothly varying
with scale, which is important for getting scaling laws.
But, at the end of the day, especially if you're not
a believer, then you need some benchmarks to really capture
real world situations, to convince people
that your language model is good.
For the believers, if I show you a remarkably slow perplexity,
they'll be convinced.
OK, any questions about perplexity?
OK.
Hopefully, everyone's a believer now.
OK, so let's talk about exam benchmarks.
So exams, as all of your students know,
is a way that we use to test humans.
And so you can adopt the same mentality
to test language models.
The nice thing about exams is that you
have a very careful control over the subject,
over the difficulty.
You can design them to have unambiguous correct answers,
which makes them easy to grade.
So there's a lot of nice properties about exams.
And so, for this reason, a lot of LM benchmarking culture
was based on just this idea of exams.
So obviously, there's been a lot of benchmarks,
but I'll just highlight some of the ones
that I think have been influential
in the development of language models.
So this one is MMLU, or Massive Multitask Language Understanding
from Hendrycks et al, 2020.
And at that time, it wasn't clear
that language models were really like general purpose task
solvers.
This was around the time when GPT-3 came out.
Many people, I think, still thought of language models
as, well, language models.
You generate fluent English.
But they had this idea that, well,
let's just try to be ahead of the curve here.
We're going to go through 57 subjects,
we're going to have a team of students
scour the internet for different sources,
and really put together this very comprehensive data set.
And despite the name MMLU, which has the word Language
Understanding, it's really about testing
knowledge and reasoning and less so just
pure language understanding.
And the way they evaluated it was with GPT-3,
using few-shot prompting.
So they essentially said, I have formed this prompt.
The following are questions about high school mathematics.
Some in-context examples of question, answer, question,
answer, and then the final question, and then the model
has to predict the answer.
So this seems very mundane.
But at that time it was, I think,
pretty radical that you would construct
this fairly complicated question and with in-context examples
and everything, and expect a language
model to actually do something reasonable.
And sure enough, at the outset, the models were not great,
I would say.
Some of the small models were barely above chance.
And the larger model-- this GPT-3--
was actually well above chance, so this was kind of encouraging.
And then over the years, as we know,
this benchmark has essentially saturated.
So this is a site I don't think this has all the data in it,
but about 3.5 Turbo.
This was like--
I guess, beginning of 2024-- oh, '23 actually--
to GPT-4.
And then, now it's in the 90s.
So there's also a link you can follow up
later on, where you can actually browse some
of the predictions of these models, which is always
fun to see what models actually goof up on
and what they get right.
OK.
So around 2024, when it seemed like MMLU, there
was a lot of progress made, it was like, OK--
you're going to see this theme again--
OK, this benchmark is getting too easy.
Let's try to make it harder.
Well, first of all, they actually
noticed that there was some noisy and trivial problems,
so let's get rid of them.
Four choices might be a little bit too easy,
so let's expand that to 10.
At that point, it was much more in vogue to use chain of thought
to solve these benchmarks, whereas when GPT-3 came out,
that wasn't really a thing.
And it's clear that some of these questions
could benefit from a few reasoning steps.
So this new benchmark was harder.
So now the accuracy of the model is back at 33.
But as you can maybe see from the progress
so far it started low.
And now it's back to I guess it's like 88 almost 90, OK.
So this benchmark might be a little bit too easy as well.
OK, so there's another benchmark called
GPQA, which stands for Google-Proof QA.
And the idea here is that OK, how can we
get a really good benchmark?
And the idea is that, well, if you can solve a problem
by looking at Google.
Google has the internet and a language model
is trained on the internet.
So if you can just solve it then that's probably too easy.
So they got some now PhD level.
So I think MMLU was think about as actually--
maybe some of these were like undergrad but maybe grad level.
But now, it's more explicitly about questions that
are meant to be pretty hard.
And at this point now you say, OK,
how do I come up with really hard questions?
You actually have to go through quite a bit of human labor
to get really hard questions.
So this was 61 PhD contractors from Upwork.
Someone writes a question.
It goes through an expert validation which then provides
feedback on the questions.
And then the question writer goes and revises the question.
And another expert looks at the question.
And then you have the question.
And then you send it to some non-experts
who are given Google access.
And then you see if they can solve the question.
So there's a subset of these questions called the DIAMOND set
that you might see in people's leaderboards
where if the two experts agree and at one of the non-experts
is able to answer the question, then that's deemed a good kind
of DIAMOND question.
So this is pretty rigorous review process.
And PhD experts were only able to get 65%.
So this is I think mostly four-way multiple choice.
So this is above random.
But this is not a good grade if you're getting 65% on an exam.
And it's not experts, even if they had 30 minutes with access
to Google, they were getting a bit over chance, but not much.
And at that point GPT-4 was like 39%,
and let's see how it's doing now.
So GPQA is now again 94.
So these benchmarks have a shelf life of not too high I guess.
I will say that some of these benchmarks,
even though they saturate the larger models,
they're still useful for developing
smaller models or fitting scaling laws and so on.
So then, yeah.
How do you know that when these tests are
being used for training and actually your models
are communicating with these?
Yeah, so this is a very important question.
So how do you know that these questions aren't
just in the training set?
So the short answer is we don't know because I don't know
what's in the training set.
I'll come back to this contamination
point a little bit later and ways of addressing it.
But you should always--
I'm glad you asked this.
You should always take these numbers
with a little bit of a grain of salt, because it's only trust.
Maybe just to say one more.
I think train contamination is a little bit subtle.
Because it's probably not the case that
they literally train on the set.
But questions can be derived from other sources.
And those sources could be trained on.
So often contamination is a much more subtle process
than literally accidentally training on the test.
Was there another question?
Same question.
OK, great.
Good always good to be skeptical.
OK, so the final exam benchmark I'll talk about
is something ominously called Humanity's Last Exam.
This is from last year.
And they were saying, OK, well these models
are getting so good.
Let's just give it all we can to create
something that's really tough.
So this is multimodal, many subjects.
It's still multiple choice.
And I guess some short answer.
So this was crowdsourced.
They had some money to incentivize people who were
into money to create questions.
They also incentivize with authorship
for those who are into that.
And they went through multiple stages of reviews
filtered by frontier models.
There's a whole process.
Another answer to your question is that they also held out
a private set that was not released publicly,
so that they could make sure that this did not
enter training.
And then you just hope that the APIs
that you-- because you still have to send this to the model,
that those prompts don't end up in the training.
But let's hope that's the case.
So every data set paper looks like this.
Previous benchmarks, look the models are doing so well.
My data set, look all the models are doing really poorly.
So this is a common pattern.
And this was especially single digits.
It's pretty abysmal here.
And let's see how we're doing in 2026.
So this one is-- it still has some room.
So it's only at--
even Mythos is only at 64.7.
So this is indeed a pretty-- it seems like a pretty hard exam.
OK, so to summarize this section, as you can see,
we've trained it towards harder and harder questions
as the models improve and we saturate existing benchmarks.
It's interesting that multiple choice format still survives
because it's--
with multiple choice, I mean, you
can make it as difficult as you want.
So some people think, well, multiple choice is too easy.
Well, I mean, I can give you a very hard
multiple-choice question.
That's not really the point.
I think more the point is that multiple choice restricts
the set of questions you can ask.
But in terms of difficulty, no problem with multiple choice.
The main problem with exam-based questions
is that this does not capture real-world usage.
No one asks HLE questions to a language model
except for when you're evaluating on HLE.
Most of the time people are asking open-ended questions.
They don't even necessarily have a correct answer.
They might not be well formed, and these benchmarks
do not capture that.
OK, so question.
How is the model output compared with the ground truth answer?
So for HLE?
For accuracy, how is the model's output
compared with the ground truth answer,
to calculate the accuracy?
To calculate the accuracy for how is the ground truth
compared.
So for multiple choice, it's just like,
did you get the right answer?
So will we check the probability distribution for each option
or how is--
So the language model generates C.
And my answer is either B or C or A or D,
and I just check if they're the same or not.
So we are only generating one token?
Yes, well, OK.
So then the question is less about evaluation.
But how does the model generate an answer?
So there's a few options.
One is that you generate--
literally you sample and it generates a letter.
Or more commonly now you generate a chain of thought.
You generate the answer maybe some explanation.
But there is a way of extracting an answer which does matter.
And language model evaluations can be very sensitive to that
but I'm not going to talk about that here.
So let's talk about a very different class of benchmarks
called chat benchmarks.
So far we've talked about multiple-choice tasks.
So they're still pretty good at capturing some notion
of intelligence and difficulty.
But most people don't ask a multiple-choice exam question
to their AI assistant unless they're
trying to use their AI system to do their exam for them,
which you would never.
One does that.
OK, so here's an example semi-inspired by a real world
use case.
So I might say I want to make a beet salad with cheese.
What herbs would work well and what wouldn't work well?
OK, so this is a very open-ended question.
And then you get some response, which is, again,
an open-ended response.
And then the question is, how do you evaluate this thing?
You can't just check exact match with equality.
There's no ground truth even.
So there's a few ideas here.
We can go through them.
So one of the ideas was pioneered by this Chatbot Arena.
And the idea is, well, you ask humans, OK.
But the way they ask humans, I think is a clever idea.
So they basically had this set of this website
where any random person from the internet can go in and chat.
And then instead of a normal as assistant
in getting one response, you actually
get two responses from two different models
which are anonymized, and then they rate which one is better.
So for example, you put in this response,
you get these two, assistant A, assistant B. And then you ask,
A is better, both are good, both are bad, B is better?
So using this process, you can get
a bunch of pairwise comparison data of model A, model B, which
one is better?
And then you can use this to compute ELO rankings
based on this.
So I don't know how many of you are familiar with this
but just get everyone on the same page.
In these ELO rankings, you define your rating model
as a probability of a particular model being
another [INAUDIBLE] model as some function of the ELO
scores of model B and model A. So the larger model ELO score
of A is the higher the probability.
So it's a smooth mapping.
And then you fit this model with the parameters,
which are the ELO ratings to maximize
the probability of the pairwise comparisons, OK.
And then as a result, you basically
get a rating for each of your models.
OK, so this is what Chatbot Arena nowadays known
as Arena AI did.
And you can get this nice ranking.
I guess Claude Opus is doing pretty well here
but some other models are on the list as well.
OK.
So there's a few things that are nice about this setup.
One is that you have real-world prompts.
So the idea is that anyone can come to the site,
and the incentive for someone to come to the site
is that they get free access to a language model.
And so there's this implicit assumption
that they're actually trying to use it to do something useful.
And therefore you get a real-world prompt.
But one thing you should keep in mind is, who are these people?
Random person on the internet is--
I don't know what that distribution.
Random person on the internet who comes to La Marina.
I don't know what that distribution looks like.
I think in their paper, they have some demographics,
but demographics don't tell the whole story.
You could worry about different biases coming
from the different models.
Maybe spammers.
People are trying to game, who maybe even submitted a model
and they want their model to look good.
You just don't know.
It's a little bit of a Wild West.
There's another issue which is that the binary preference,
which is better, A or B is very nice and simple
and feeds into this rating, but does conflate style
and correctness.
So ELO ratings for chess makes a lot of sense,
because the only thing that matters is, did you win?
But which one is better is much less clear cut.
And there's questions of the human is the judge here.
The person who puts in the prompt
is answering the question.
And this is good because in some level,
because the person has some intent
and they can declare whether their intent was met.
To some extent, except for they're
presumably asking the question because they
don't know the answer.
So if I give you two answers, how
are they to judge which one is correct?
And then there's also the problem of sycophancy,
where maybe more pleasing answers
are going to be upweighted highly compared
to correct but honest answers.
So there's a lot of potential issues here.
But the nice thing about this method, which
is that you don't need to feed the same
prompts to all the models, and this is the beauty of ELO.
In chess, you don't have to play.
Everyone plays everyone else.
It can just be some sparse sample of that.
And you can still derive rankings as long
as the graph is connected.
And this is important because human is rating
and you can't expect a human to rate all the models
or even more than two models.
And the nice thing as well is that
as new prompts and new models come in,
there's a natural story for making this updating over time.
So let me talk about a different approach.
So this is AlpacaEval from 2023.
There were some instructions derived from various sources.
And the metric here is the win rate against a baseline model.
So you have a model, AlpacaEval says,
I'm going to generate it for a prompt,
generate using let's say baseline model GPT-4
preview at that time and then judge using GPT preview, which
one is better?
So immediately, this raises a question of potential bias.
But let's put that aside for now.
So this is basically an instantiation
of LLM as a judge, which is very popular these days
for evaluating language models.
And you can mitigate this bias by having
multiple judges and ensembling and so on and so forth.
So one problem with initial AlpacaEval
is that LLM judges favor long responses.
And this led to a bunch of leaderboard gaming
where a bunch of models that were fine tuned were submitted
and they got really high LLM AlpacaEval
performance just because the responses were longer.
So this got fixed in a subsequent paper where
the use a very simple regression method to de-bias the metric.
OK, but this raises a more general question here,
which is not necessarily specific to AlpacaEval which is,
how do you evaluate a metric?
So we've been talking about evaluation of models.
And if I have a metric, how you can evaluate a model.
But if I'm coming up with a metric,
how do this metric is any good?
So this is a hard problem.
And there's no answer here.
One thing you can do is more of a sanity check
is you can look at correlation with other metrics
with the idea that higher isn't necessarily better in all cases
unless you are trying to mimic this other metric.
So AlpacaEval correlation with Chatbot Arena
is 0.98 which is quite high.
So which suggests that you could--
let's say you wanted to evaluate on a Chatbot Arena,
but you're too shy to put your model
or you don't want to wait for humans or whatever,
you can use AlpacaEval to evaluate instead.
Now, this correlation, of course,
is with respect to a certain set of models.
And so this might not hold for models
that let's say are stronger than GPT-4 preview.
So at this point, this leaderboard I don't think
is really--
hasn't been maintained in over a year but this
is what it looked like at that time.
So there's another benchmark I'll talk about,
which is WildBench and this one was sourced a bunch of examples
from human-chatbot conversations.
So like Chatbot Arena, they also put up a free service
where people could chat with this bot
and they collected the queries.
And then like AlpacaEval, they used LLM as a judge
to evaluate the model.
The main innovation here is the use
of a checklist, which is generated
and specific to a particular prompt or task.
And the idea here is that if you just
ask a language model to judge whether this response is good
or not.
This is in some sense a very ill-defined task.
I don't know what depends on what you care about.
And so the idea here is that by having a checklist or some
of rubric, this greatly scopes and makes the task evaluation
task more well-defined.
So they did this, also, they showed correlation
with Chatbot Arena which admittedly
is a little bit circular because then you can ask why, well,
is Chatbot Arena really the ground truth?
But at least we're all in the same boat together.
OK, so to conclude this section, how do you
evaluate open-ended responses?
There's no clear solution here but there's some ideas.
Pairwise comparisons between a reference and a model response
is generally a good idea because especially
for very similar responses, you can
give directional information.
Well, this one's slightly better than this.
But in terms of absolute ranking like is this a 7 out of 10
or a 8 out of 10?
That tends to be a lot less high signal.
One should always be aware of biases
both in terms of humans or LLM judges.
They have different biases, but nonetheless that's
something important to pay attention to.
Perhaps the only thing you might be able to do
is you evaluate over multiple judges, humans,
and judges of all everything is saying
your model is better than--
maybe your model is better.
And finally, the evaluation problem here
of open-ended response.
I would emphasize is not really well-defined.
And so increasingly, I think it's
important to define rubrics or checklists to improve
the reliability or well-definedness
of an actual evaluation.
And this is true regardless of a human and a judge.
So anyone who's done crowdsourcing
knows that if you just ask a human to rate
something without giving some of rubric,
you're probably going to get very nonsensical results.
OK, so let's move on to the agentic world.
So you can think about what we've
been doing so far is evaluate what language models say,
and that's chat.
And now, we're going to evaluate what LLMs do, which is agents.
And so for anyone who's following AI hype,
agents are everywhere.
And these are-- definitely, I think
going to transform the way that we think about language models.
So Agent is basically a language model
plus some scaffold, which is a logic for deciding
how the language model is going to be called
and what tools it can has access to and so on and so forth.
So there's a few benchmarks I want to just point out
that are authentic.
So one is very popular.
It's just called SWE-bench.
Basically, the task is you're given
a code base and a description of a GitHub issue, submit a PR.
And the way you evaluate a PR is whether it passes the unit test.
So these tests are designed so that before you submit a PR,
certain unit tests don't pass.
And then your goal is to fix it.
So certain unit tests pass and you don't break anything else.
So here's an example of some instructions.
Here's the issue.
And then some code that is provided in the context.
And then your goal is to generate a patch.
And given a patch you are evaluated on
whether you pass or not.
So the good thing about this is that the evaluation
is very straightforward.
And let's see how we're doing on SWE-bench.
Actually, this is going to be SWE-bench Verified which
later I'll show you, tell you why this happened.
So SWE-bench in-- this was only I
guess 2024 was still around 16% and now it's up to 93.
Good job Mythos.
So this is a very canonical generic benchmark,
as a lot of the attention on agents
has been invested in coding abilities.
So SWE-bench really pioneered this way
of thinking about how to assess an agent's ability
to write and code in a realistic environment.
So here's another project called Terminal-Bench.
And here the idea is that this is going
to be more general purpose.
And we're going to basically have the environment be
a computer terminal.
And we're going to define a bunch of tasks
that can be done in a computer terminal
by typing in a bunch of commands.
And the nice thing about this environment
is a very simple and universal.
And these tasks were crowdsourced from 93 people
from across the world.
89 of these tasks are constitute Terminal-Bench 2.0.
These tasks generally take ranging from one hour
to over a week, depending on whether you're
an expert or a junior.
And then, here's what the leaderboard
looks like as of today.
So top models are the frontier models.
One thing that's interesting is that the agent is also important
here because you can have two agents but the same model
and they have different accuracies.
So another benchmark I'll talk about is Cybersecurity.
So this is 40 Capture The Flag tasks.
And the setting here is that you have
an agent that is given an environment
and it can run various commands like look at the source code.
It can access the web server.
And the goal is to essentially hack into this server
to extract some flag, which is a unique string that
proves that you've hacked into the server.
So these are competitions, cybersecurity exercises that
are done by humans normally.
And this is an example of what the agent
scaffold looks like here.
This is a very simplistic version where basically you
have one continuous memory.
You produce some action, you get environment feedback,
and then you put the results into this buffer
and this is concatenated.
As I'll show you later, this history
obviously grows quite a bit.
And you'll need to have better ways of managing context.
So this is what the leaderboard looks like when it came out.
The best models were around 10% or so.
And over time now it's completely solved actually.
So that's CyBench.
There's another class of problems
which are MLE engineering.
So this benchmark has a bunch of Kaggle competitions
which involve processing data, training models,
and so on and so forth.
And the agent can look at the data set, read the description,
write code, train models, and you eventually submit something
and you get a grade.
So this is what the leaderboard looks like right now.
And again, you can see that it's really the same usual suspects
on the LLM side.
But there's quite a bit of variation
in terms of the different agent scaffolds.
So one thing to note about, I'll point out
about agent scaffolds is that they matter a lot.
So when I said I talk about language model evaluation,
this is a broader than language model evaluation.
And the reason is that unlike what I mentioned before
with this earliest CyBench agent scaffold, now
you have to be a lot more sophisticated to solve
really complicated tasks.
One thing that people realize is that explicit planning
is helpful.
You can't just stream of consciousness,
chain of thought this.
And then you build up this context
and the agent can easily lose track of where it is.
So instead of keep a to-do list, get it checked off.
Hierarchical delegation, agents should call other sub-agents
with some clean context.
And that agent does some stuff and returns only the result.
The master agent doesn't need to see all the gory details,
and this can help encapsulate, provide some encapsulation.
Memory, people have been experimenting around
with explicitly reading and writing files,
especially as the context grows.
You can't just store it in your context window.
And then finally, there is more context engineering in the style
of managing the process.
When should you delegate to sub-agents?
When to try this strategy versus this other strategy, what
to write persistent memory.
And these things are generally optimized
for the particular language model.
So agents are exciting because they enhance the capability
surface of language models.
Scaffolds are very important.
So really, when we talk about evaluating agents,
it's evaluating both the language model
and the agent scaffold.
Now, we're going to switch gears a little bit
and talk about this other very different style of benchmarks.
I call them pure reasoning for lack of a better term.
And the motivation is that all the tasks so far require
some linguistic and world knowledge.
And so the question is, can we just
isolate reasoning or pure fluid intelligence
from a knowledge and knowing facts?
And you could argue that this gives you
a form of more pure intelligence.
So there was this project, ARC-AGI,
which started back in 2019, where the goal was exactly this.
So the task was meant to be 100% solvable by humans,
but challenging for AIs.
And every task is a special snowflake or that's the intent.
And so memorizing a bunch of facts
or solving previous problems shouldn't really
help you that much.
So if you guys are remembering your LLM history,
2019 was pre-LLM.
I mean this was GPT-2 era.
So this was prescient in that regard.
So here's an example of the first iteration of that problem.
You're given these pictures and you're
trying to guess what comes next.
And if you take 10 seconds, you can probably solve this problem.
So you probably guess it's to just fill in the yellow
to form the rectangle.
So then last year, there was an updated version
of this task, which was a bit more complicated.
And you can take a look at this.
So here's the trajectory.
So when ARC-AGI-1 came out--
I think this is actually 0.
So basically models didn't do anything.
So there's GPT-3-- pre-trained model didn't
move the needle at all, right.
And this was exactly as the creators had intended.
Pre-trained models just learn what
the facts are on the internet and maybe learn
linguistic patterns.
But none of that is actually helpful directly,
at least for these ARC-AGI tasks.
And then something happened in 2024.
And this is when OpenAI released their o1 and o3 models.
Then things started taking off pretty abruptly.
And now, ARC-AGI-1 is basically solved.
And even around 2025 when ARC-AGI-2 came out,
this has also-- it's not quite solved,
but it looks like it's on its way to being solved.
So it was really the reasoning capabilities that unlocked this.
And now one could wonder whether all the knowledge
of actual pre-training was necessary for this task.
And certainly, without pre-training
we wouldn't have this explosion of reasoning models.
So arguably it was still important,
but not maybe directly visible for much
of the history of ARC-AGI.
So now, just last month, ARC-AGI-3 comes out.
So you see this familiar pattern.
Our creators look at this and it's like, oh,
time for a new benchmark.
So this is now an interactive environment
where you can go online and you can play this game.
So again, no language.
You're just trying to figure out, based on patterns.
It's kind of fun.
And now the scores are extremely low.
So next year when I teach this class,
I'm sure I'll have to update this slide.
But we'll see.
So I think this ARC-AGI line is a really interesting
to think about.
The goal is to disentangle reasoning from knowledge.
This is really hard to do.
And it's not--
I think this is probably the best attempt at this.
It's not clear whether you can really fully decouple things.
And certainly, if people really cared about this benchmark,
I think people probably could--
people can benchmark I think probably anything.
So you could design questions like,
are these-- these still come from some prior
and not sure there's anything as quote unquote pure as reasoning.
This is also constrained to human reasoning.
The explicit goal is to be 100% human solvable
within some reasonable time.
So this doesn't really extend to superhuman reasoning,
for example [INAUDIBLE] winning more gold medals
or solving open math problems, which arguably are still
very useful and important.
But clearly this exposes some gaps in the current models.
So there is work to do if you think about the goal
as basically being able to solve all the tasks.
So this ARC-AGI-3 especially looks quite graphic.
So is there some multimodal content involved or encoding
or as a textual representation as well?
Yeah so the question is this looks very graphical.
And so what is the input to a language model?
So this is essentially--
I don't know what the--
I think it's 64 by 64.
So you can provide this image, or you
can provide it in Ascii Art or some of textual representation.
Either way, there is a spatial element here
that the model has to reason about, which is really not
English or natural language.
So let's talk about shift gears and talk
about another class of benchmarks
which is related to safety.
So people have been talking about safety
in language models for a while.
And if you think about other areas such as cars,
it's pretty clear what safety means here.
These ratings for safety ratings for cars,
which involve testing based on smashing cars
into a wall with an airbag and seeing
how well it does and protects the dummies in the car.
And this is with decades of lobbying and figuring out
what safety means for vehicles.
So what does it mean for AI?
So I would say that there is not a great answer here,
but I'll give you some examples of what people
have been thinking about.
So there's this benchmark called Harm-Bench.
And this is really about prompting a model with things
that are meant to be harmful and expecting the model
to essentially refuse.
So this is one type of safety.
And I think probably the dominant thing
when people think about safety is
that I want to prevent bad actors from doing things
with language models, but it turns out
that's not the only thing that matters.
So there's this other work, AIR-Bench,
which tries to think about safety holistically
by looking at all the regulatory frameworks in the EU, China,
and the US company policies and builds
a taxonomy of all the different things that could go wrong.
And then using this, constructing
a particular set of prompts and evaluating
and so on and so forth.
But one problem with safety is, jailbreaking,
which is its own sub problem, which
is that language models are generally trained
to refuse harmful instructions.
But as we know you can get around this if you're clever.
And so there's some early work that
uses automatic ways to optimize for prompts to bypass safety
using GCG, which is basically this coordinate
wise optimization algorithm.
And remarkably, optimizing on open models
allows us to transfer to models.
So I hope this doesn't these attacks don't work anymore.
But at the time, you can generate some basically
gibberish and step by step plan to destroy humanity
and OpenAI's model will comply.
Obviously, you could argue, well,
is this actually harmful plan to destroy humanity?
At least it did not-- the expected behavior is that it
should probably refuse that.
So this raises a bigger problem which is, what is safety?
And one thing that makes this tricky
is that many aspects of safety are very contextual.
So it involves politics, law, social norms.
This varies across different countries.
And then also, if you think about safety,
you have to think about what are the risks.
And the risks are actually quite varied as well
and demand probably different attention.
So hallucinations is a risk, especially
let's say a medical or legal or financial settings.
But this is also correlated with just capabilities.
If you make a model more accurate,
it's correlated with not who is seeing as much.
Sycophancy is a problem.
Abetting crimes is a problem.
But this might be counter to capabilities, inequality.
Losing critical thinking might be a risk as well that correlate
with capability.
So if you think about the societal impact of language
models on the world and think about safety
as ensuring that AI goes well for people,
this is actually a much more complex topic
than I'll have time to talk about.
And finally, there is a dual use aspect of language models.
So the cybersecurity agents can be used to hack into a system
or to do penetration testing and make systems more secure, which
makes talking about whether these are safety risks
or actually beneficial a double-edged sword.
OK, so let's move on now to talk about some broader
considerations of evaluation.
So one thing that I think is an important aspect of evaluation
is realism or ecological validity.
How well does evaluation capture real-world use?
So in particular exams are very far away from real-world use.
Chatbot Arena are from real people
but one could wonder whether this distribution is
the right distribution of people or use cases or not.
There's a few benchmarks I'll mention
that try to get at ecological validity,
and in particular at the use case level,
at least not the individual query level.
So OpenAI created benchmark called GDPVal.
They looked at all the top nine sectors
according to US GDP, 44 different occupations,
got a bunch of professionals to create tasks.
These are professionals with about 14 years of experience.
And you can see people who are nurses who work concierge,
real estate agents, film and video editors
and so on and so forth.
And they created a bunch of tasks.
Here's another example.
In the medical domain where up until this point,
a lot of medical benchmarks were based on standardized exams.
And in fact, actually for humans,
this is also what happens.
You take these standardized exams
and you graduate from med school and then you go operate on.
Well, actually, there's a longer process.
You don't operate on patients directly.
But the point is that for a language model,
you should also not just pass medical exams
and deploy them directly.
So this was a project where 121 tasks were
sourced from 29 clinicians.
And this was meant to represent the type of things
that clinicians would actually ask to a language model, which
are quite different than the multiple choice
type of exam questions.
Here's another project which gets at real data.
So if you ask, who actually has the data
on what people are doing?
Well, it's the model developers.
And so this project is interesting
because it uses language models themselves to analyze real data.
So in particular, you do to privacy.
You can't literally go and look at people's data,
but you can have language models look at the data
and analyze and summarize general patterns.
So then the language models could tell you
about what are the types of people--
what are the types of things that people use Claude for?
And sometimes realism and privacy
are at odds with each other because ideally you
would want actually a sample from the actual query stream.
And that would be very valuable to assess
how well a model is working and understand deeply
what the errors are.
But then that runs into privacy considerations.
OK, so another consideration, which
is another type of validity is just in general,
how do that the evaluations are scientifically valid?
And this was brought up fairly early, train-test overlap
or contamination.
So in a machine learning 101, you
learn don't train on your test set hopefully.
And before foundation models this
was actually pretty clear right.
So with ImageNet and SQuAD and many benchmarks
sorry, data sets, there was always a train split
and a test split and everyone played the same game.
You train on your training data, you test on your test data.
Life was simple.
And now, you have these models that
are trained on the internet.
And much more than that.
And furthermore, you don't what's in the data.
So this makes evaluation quite different I think.
So what can you do in this?
So first thing you can do is you can
try to infer whether a model has actually seen the test data.
So this is a neat idea from Tatsu's group
where you leverage the fact that the order
in which the questions in the benchmark occurs
should be random.
But if the model prefers some particular order that's
consistent with the benchmark, that is probably--
it's just trained on that benchmark.
Another route is that you can encourage people to report
actual train-test overlap.
So this has to do with norms.
I think in general, especially maybe less in machine learning,
but more in statistics you always
report confidence intervals.
You have an estimate.
And I always want to know, how reliable is that estimate?
This is just standard practice.
And so the idea of this position paper
is that you should model providers.
If you're going to claim some GPQA score,
you should always provide some justification
that you didn't train on the test set.
So another route is that where you can just give up.
It's like OK, all these evaluations there--
let's just assume that people trained on them, let's
assume the worst case.
So the thing that we have on our side
is that you can always define fresh evals.
So there's a bunch of ideas, LiveCodeBench, UncheeatableEval,
which basically scrape new web pages or archive
papers or GitHub and defines evaluations populations that
are past the cutoff date of the language models.
So this seems pretty robust and good.
But one thing to keep in mind is that time stamps
aren't always safe either, because I might
post with code for example.
I might put something on GitHub which is actually
derived from some other repo.
And so how do that's actually generally fresh?
Route 4 is to use private evaluations.
So companies' model developers do this right.
So if you're Google or OpenAI you have your internal code
base, which you assume is not on the internet,
and you obviously wouldn't train on this data,
so you can use it for evaluation.
So this generally is pretty reliable.
And if you're not a company, you can use your personal writings.
I have a bunch of rejected papers from when
I was in grad school that I never put on online,
so I can use those.
And this type of evaluation, I think,
is very favorable for perplexity evals,
because all you need in perplexity
is just you need a good data set and you
can evaluate log probabilities.
So another concern that I'll mention is data set quality.
So remember I showed the leaderboard
for SWE-Bench Verified.
This is because, well, SWE-Bench had
a bunch of problems of tasks, unit tests that
weren't quite rigorous enough and other things that got fixed.
And there are many other benchmarks that have gone
through this process like GSM8K or MMLU,
where people have gone and done a more careful audit and realize
that, wait a minute, this question actually doesn't--
something's broken around this question.
So like this one.
There's no curve given in this text
so you can't answer this question.
Does the baby have socks on?
No, there's no way to tell.
And there's also this paper that showed that there's
a lot of problems with the agentic benchmarks, which
arguably are even harder to assess because it's not just
you can look at the question and the possible answers
and you can look at it but there's a whole environment.
And there are cases where with coding you can
it's great to have test cases that either pass or not passed.
But as we all test cases can be incomplete.
So you might pass all the test cases
but still not have a working solution.
There's another case of this TorchBench benchmark
where they show that if an agent just outputs the empty response,
they can get a 38%.
So there are some trivialities with these benchmarks
that you want have to be very careful to avoid.
One thing I'll call out is that there's
this tool called Docent that uses
language models to inspect agent traces to detect problems.
So this is a qualitative response
to our very quantitative heavy way of benchmarking.
And I would always recommend that whenever
you do a benchmark, either develop a benchmark
or run a model on the benchmark that you always
look at the output and try to audit it to make sure
that you actually think you're measuring what
you think you're measuring.
OK, so maybe getting a bit more philosophical.
So what's the point of evaluation?
OK.
So I've talked a lot about different types of evaluation.
And really, there's no one evaluation to rule them all.
And I think it's-- when you're thinking about evaluation,
you have to be very clear about what the purpose is.
And I think often this is not really stated clearly.
So for example, you could be a user,
or a company that's trying to make a purchase decision.
Are you going to go with A or B for a particular use case?
Or you're just a researcher and you
have this intuitive notion of intelligence
and you want to measure it somehow.
Or you want to understand the benefits and harms for business
or policy reasons.
Or you're a developer and you want to get feedback
to improve the model.
So each of these goals will lead you
to potentially different benchmarks or some combination
of evaluation strategies.
And finally, one thing to address,
which I hinted at briefly, is that
what are we even evaluating?
So before foundation models, researchers evaluated methods
because we have these trained test splits.
And the only thing that was varying is the actual algorithm.
And today, we're mostly evaluating models and systems
where anything goes.
There are some exceptions.
So the NanoGPT speedrun is deliberately
a way to evaluate an algorithm, in particular, how well fast you
can train a model.
But most of language model evaluation
is about evaluating the actual end model, which is useful
because that is the thing that is actually going to get shipped
and people are going to use.
But I think the punchline is that you should always
be very deliberate about declaring what your goals are.
OK, so there's no one true evaluation.
Choose what you're trying to measure.
And we talked about a bunch of different benchmarks
starting with perplexity, exam based, chat, agentic, reasoning,
and safety.
They vary in terms of difficulty, realism,
how valid they are.
And there's often trade offs.
It's hard to have really real and difficult and ecologically
valid.
And no trade tests contamination.
So often you have to compromise on one of these factors,
and depending on your goals, you will
have to choose which one you're willing to compromise on.
So that is the end of this lecture.
So next week, we're going to start
talking about training data.
[AUDIO LOGO]
OK, see you next time.