So last lecture, Percy covered some
of the underlying mechanics, let's call it, of parallelism.
Today, I'm going to do my favorite thing of talk
about all sorts of things you can know, like knowledge,
details, and trivia about how modern parallelism for language
model training works.
And what we're going to try to do
is really get to grips with the many, many complexities that
are involved when you are having to train
huge models on huge clusters.
It's going to turn out that there
are many different parallelization strategies
that you can use at once.
At the end, we will get to a slide where I say 4D
parallelism, because there's four different things that you
can do at once.
Actually, even more that I'll talk about.
And it turns out that to parallelize at the largest
scale, you'll need to use all of them or most of them.
And we'll discuss why.
Part of your assignment will be figuring out,
given a particular network topology and a particular model,
what is the optimal parallelization
strategy for that?
And then finally, I'll walk through some examples
of recent large scale training runs
with details that are published and show
you this stuff in action.
OK, so the very first part, I'll go through somewhat quickly.
It's partially a review of basic collectives, basic networking
primitives, right.
But the reason why we need all of this parallelism stuff
is because there's going to be two bottlenecks that we'll
solve by going to multiple machines and multiple GPUs.
So one of it is compute.
We need more compute than we can bring to bear on a single chip.
And the way we solve that is just to have many, many machines
and link them up together.
Right, the fastest supercomputers in the world
have exaflops of compute, whereas a single GPU
is nowhere near that number.
The other reason why we need to continue to scale in parallel
is because of memory, right.
Models are big.
We can't fit them all into one GPU,
so we need to shard them into smaller pieces somehow.
So this is going to lead to complexities
of having many GPUs across many different machines.
And an important conceptual object
that we will deal with throughout our lecture today
is the difference between intranode parallelism,
where your connections are very fast,
and so you can do things that are very communication
expensive.
And you're going to have slower internode communication.
And because these are slow, we will
have to use processes that respect the communication
constraints of our channel more, right.
So we're going to have to do both of those.
And remember all of the things that we will do today.
We're not actually going to be sending packets or anything
like that.
We're going to be dealing with this
at the level of collective communication primitives.
Right, so whenever we do accounting
for how much communication is done,
I might say, OK, we're going to have to do all-reduce
or we're going to have to do allgather to implement
some of these operations.
So in order to implement some of these efficiently,
you're going to have to go all the way to the hardware level.
But our discussion today is going to be algorithmic.
And so all of the networking primitives I'll talk about
is going to be at this level of a collective.
And remember, Percy talked about this,
but this is important for--
very important for one part of the talk, which
is going to be that the equivalence
between all-reduce and reduce-scatter plus all-gather.
Right, so there's going to be one algorithm where on one hand,
you do an all-reduce, and on the other hand,
you do two of these different steps.
And the fact that these two have the same cost in some sense
means that we can do the algorithm on the right for free.
We'll see that again later.
This is just a quick refresher just
to make sure you remember what Percy said.
OK, so that's it for the really basic review.
The other thing I want to touch on briefly
before we get into the algorithms,
which are going to be hardware and substrate agnostic,
is the difference-- oh, sorry, yes?
[INAUDIBLE] reduce scatter and--
Is there any particular reason why you are saying that old
OK, the question was, is there any reason why I'm talking
about this specifically?
[INAUDIBLE]
We will--
Yes, yes, there are other decompositions.
This one in particular will be useful for a algorithm, which
is why I'm emphasizing this particular decomposition.
That's right.
There's others that you could do, of course.
Yes.
OK.
So the other thing I will talk about before I start--
most of our discussion today will be hardware agnostic.
For the most part, once you understand the basic concepts,
you'll be able to apply it to any hardware substrate.
But I do want to briefly before we start,
just talk about the low level hardware stack.
Both because it's interesting.
But also because I think it leads
to different parallelization strategies
across different model training companies.
So remember the TPU.
Right, TPU is Google's accelerator.
And I mentioned during the GPU lecture,
a TPU is like a lightweight GPU.
But what's different is the networking.
So how is the networking different?
Well, in one slide, the TPU network
is what's called a toroidal mesh.
Right, so you can think about a grid
and then allowing the ends of the grid
to communicate with each other.
It's a little bit more complicated.
It's a 3D picture.
Which, Marcel, you have the visualization, right?
Can you post that in the lecture channel?
Yeah.
So there's a fun web visualization that you can look
at that visualizes the toroidal mesh in 3D, which is very cool.
But your mental model, I think, can roughly be this picture.
You can forget the more complex one.
All the chips are networked to neighbors and the neighbors wrap
around, right.
So what does this let you do?
This lets you have a very simple networking
topology that can be indefinitely scaled up very
simply, right.
The number of neighbors you have is the same, no matter
how large your network gets.
In contrast, the GPU networking philosophy is very different.
It's really much more of an all to all philosophy.
And the way that it's networked is it's like a tree.
It's often called a fat tree.
You have your GPUs connected very,
very quickly at the lowest layers.
And then you have groups of GPUs that are connected in a pod.
And then the pods might have spine switches
that allow them to communicate to each other.
And this means that as the number of nodes grows,
the tree gets bigger and bigger.
Your communication costs is going to get higher,
or your communication topology will get more complicated,
because you're connecting all these all to all as you go.
Now, this difference in philosophy
means that if you're communicating only to neighbors,
TPUs are great.
They're cost effective.
And you can make each connection more beefy,
right, with the same power consumption.
But if you're connecting in very random ways, very stochastic,
unpredictable ways, then this GPU networking
will be more flexible, right.
So there's this very different design philosophy
that you see between TPUs and GPUs.
And I'll try to mention where this shows up
as we go through the parallelism lecture.
And I posted this into the lecture chat last lecture.
Because someone asked, what's the difference
between these two and so on?
Right, but just to back up my point, Bill Daley and Jeff Dean
were talking about the different hardware and what
are they good for, right.
GPUs are good for things like mixture of experts, where
the communication is much less clear because tokens
route to different experts.
TPUs are great if you have this dense model
that you're doing very predictable partitions of.
I'll talk about that in an idea called tensor parallelism later
in this lecture.
And so these hardware things are good for different workloads.
And this was where I was going to leave it for the lecture
until this morning, when Google decided
that they were going to announce TPU8i and t this morning.
And then I looked at this as I was preparing my lecture,
and I said, oh my god, TPu8i?
That's a tree topology.
They've switched to a much more all to all connection.
And if you think about it, it makes sense.
Modern day language models are MoEs.
And if you're going to serve a MoE,
you're going to have all sorts of bandwidth
just flying around as you route tokens to different experts.
You probably do want much more of an all to all
connectivity where, at inference time,
these communications are real bottlenecks.
You want to deal with them.
And even at training time, the TPU8t, which is a training chip,
the cross rack connectivity looks a lot more like a GPU.
There's much more like an all to all style
switch that's being built out called the Virgo network.
That's a higher level networking stack.
So I think there's really interesting things happening.
It's a little bit of a convergent evolution
across both TPUs and GPUs, where really the workloads are
defining the network that we need to have.
OK.
And then the final thing about hardware--
I just love talking about what's happening in the Chinese AI
scene-- is this idea of--
I think in the GPU lecture, someone
asked, if SRAM is so good, why don't you just all use SRAM?
Only SRAM chip.
And that's Grok, right?
It works really well.
Now, some of you might be thinking,
if all to all connectivity is good, why don't you just
connect everything and connect them with really fast fiber
optic chips, right?
And then you would get the Huawei Ascend 910, right?
So if you look at the specs of the Huawei Ascend,
it's actually really interesting,
because each chip is a lot worse than a H200.
It's a lot slower at matmuls.
It's slower in many ways.
But then, if you're willing to dedicate a giant rack of fiber
optic switches to connect a much larger number of chips,
like in their case, 384 in a big rack,
then maybe you can deal with the fact
that each chip is slower by just connecting a much, much larger
number of these guys, right.
And then so I think what this shows
us is a really interesting tradeoff.
Because once you look at this architecture,
you realize the power consumption of this thing
is insanely high.
It's four times that of the equivalent NVIDIA system.
And so it's something like, well,
if you're willing to pay the power cost,
you can solve a lot of communication problems
brute force, and you can scale out much more aggressively
to 300 chips.
But you're paying a power cost, right.
It's similar to that SRAM story of,
if you want to design a hardware that
is efficient to use both power and manufacturing wise,
you end up in a certain place.
If you want to brute force things,
you end up in a very different place.
Right, so this is, I think, just a very interesting place
to learn from about these hardware design tradeoffs.
OK, good.
So now, just to put this all together,
the first thing you should think about is the new unit of compute
is not the GPU.
It's the entire data center.
And we want to have several things.
We want to be able to control the amount of memory we use.
We want to be able to control the amount of compute
that we can bring to bear.
And we want all of these to be lossless.
Right, we want to use all of the resources that we have.
And then we're going to talk about the algorithms that
will enable this through all these communication
primitives components.
OK, good.
So now the second part of this lecture
is going to be the bulk of the content.
And these are the algorithms that we will use
to paralyze language models.
And there's going to be a couple of different important ideas.
Actually, we should probably maybe even be grouped.
Data parallel is one set of ideas for essentially
taking your data that you're going to train on
and distributing them across GPUs.
So the data is the ones that move around.
And then model parallelism, you're
going to chop up different parts of the model
and split them around.
Turns out that the boundary between these two
is a little leaky, because one of the algorithms
here will actually cut parameters up, too.
But we will see why I've put all of these algorithms
into these different bins, right.
And conceptually, we're trying to both scale
out compute and memory, and that's
why we will need a whole bunch of these different tricks.
Cool.
All right.
So data parallelism, I think, is the easiest to understand.
It is conceptually very simple, and I
think it's the standard way that you would try to parallelize
an algorithm like LLM training.
So forget that we're doing Adam.
We're going to do just naive SGD for the moment.
Then we have a capital B sized batch, right.
So each update step, I'm going to take capital B elements,
and I'm going to sum up the gradients.
And I'll take my update, right.
So the most naive form of parallelism
that one can do for this is to take my batch,
B. I can cut it up across M machines.
If they're divisible, each machine
will get a smaller B over M sized batch.
And then what I'm going to do is each machine computes gradients,
and then I will synchronize all the gradients to get my sum.
OK, great.
So compute scaling wise, this is perfect.
As long as there's enough examples per GPU, we're good.
Communications overhead.
How much do we have to talk to each other?
Well, every batch, we have to basically communicate
two times the number of parameters, right.
Because what I have to do is I have to basically communicate
my gradients back and forth.
OK, and then for memory scaling, there's absolutely none.
Every GPU has the same copies of the models.
You need to have the same sized activations
so you don't save any memory at all in this scheme.
So now what is the problem?
Clearly we've addressed compute to some extent.
But we have not addressed memory at all.
So let's take a look at this memory problem
and just do a little bit of accounting.
Initially, it might seem that the memory situation is bad.
But it turns out our memory situation is actually
just terrible.
And the reason why the memory situation is terrible
is if you just do some parameter accounting, right,
it just turns out you need to store a lot of stuff.
Right, and not only do we need to store a lot of stuff,
it's actually more than the parameters
that we need to store.
So roughly the rule of thumb-- it depends on your precision.
But the rule of thumb, you might say,
is that we need something like five copies of weights
and 16 bytes per parameter to store our model.
So we will need to, of course, store our model parameters.
We need a place to put our gradients, right.
The accumulator before we put them into the model parameters.
So we need to store those guys.
But actually, you need to maybe store more stuff.
You might need to have a higher precision accumulator that you
accumulate into in SGD.
This might be temporary, but you might need this.
And if you're doing Adam, and this is really
where the bad stuff comes in, you're
going to need to track both the first and second moments
of your gradients.
And you need to track them over time, right.
So you need two of these.
And unfortunately, you might need
to store them in high precision depending on your stability
characteristics.
And these might be quite expensive, right.
And we generally call these things optimizer state.
Right, the thing that you're accumulating into.
The first moment, the second moment.
Right, and these are actually quite expensive.
If you look at the accounting, this
is most of the cost memory wise of doing an SGD update.
And so I think one of the really elegant and nice things
that you can do in this space is to start
cutting up the amount of memory you need
and distributing them across the accelerators,
but doing so in this structured way that gets you
these gains for basically free.
So as I said in the last slide, the optimizer state
is most of your memory.
So here, the optimizer state is green.
That's most of your memory.
Orange is your gradients, and blue is your parameters.
And notice how parameters and gradients are the same size,
and your state is bigger, right.
If you do naive data parallel, you're
just going to replicate all of this state across the GPUs.
And this is not so good, right.
Because you've, in some sense, consumed way
more memory than you need and your memory consumption
is linear with your number of accelerators.
Not so good, right.
What we can do instead is perhaps
we can shard the optimizer state onto different GPUs.
And this would be a big savings.
If we shard different other parts of what we need to track,
that would be also big savings.
Maybe we can also shard the gradients into different GPUs.
Or in the extreme, maybe we can shard everything
into different accelerators.
And then you can see that the implied memory
gains on the very right would be quite dramatic as we go all
the way down from 120 to 1.9.
Now, the main thing that we will study now
is, what is the cost of doing this?
Right, you might imagine, there's no free lunch.
Baseline is going to be the fastest.
And as we go downwards to here, we're
going to have to pay a big communication cost in order
to achieve these memory savings.
I think the remarkable thing is going to be that a lot of this
will be free.
But I'm going to walk through this step by step.
So let's start with what people call ZeRO stage 1.
So there's going to be three stages corresponding to each
of these steps.
And so stage 1 is going to be the simplest.
The only thing I will shard is my optimizer state.
And I will shard it across the GPUs, OK.
Everyone is going to have both the parameters
and the gradients.
And so what you can think of is each worker
is going to be responsible for updating
one slice of the parameter.
So if I'm GPU number 0, my responsibility
is updating this very first slice over here.
And I'm not responsible for any of the other updates.
So how would it work?
Right, so what we're going to do is everyone computes.
Everyone has a different data item, right.
So they're going to compute a full gradient on their data
item.
That's the first step.
Now I'm going to take the gradient I computed
and I'm going to reduce scatter the gradients onto all
the other machines.
Because everyone else needs my gradients, right?
But they don't need all the gradients.
They only need the gradients associated with their update.
Right, so every worker is going to get from me, my gradient,
but they're part of the parameter space, right.
So this is going to be equivalent to a number
of parameters communication costs.
Because I'm sending my gradient, but I'm cutting it up
and sending it into each GPU.
Now each machine is going to be able to now do their update.
They have their parameters, they have their gradients
that they got from everybody else,
and they have their own state that they've tracked, right.
And now, the parameters have been updated.
And now I'm going to all gather them back.
Right, I was responsible for, let's
say, one fourth of the parameters.
So those updated parameters, I'm going to send back
to everybody else, right.
So this is a all-gather, right.
So this is where the equivalence is useful.
How many operations did I do?
Well, in the naive data parallel case, what I had to do
was I had to do one all-reduce.
Right, I had to exchange all the gradients with everybody
and then do the updates, right.
So the communication cost is 2 times the parameters.
Now in ZeRO stage 1, I did two operations.
One was a reduce-scatter to send the gradients out
and then an all-gather to collect the updated parameters.
But we already said a reduce-scatter and an all-gather
is equivalent to an all-reduce.
So ZeRO stage 1 is going to have the exact same communication
characteristics as naive DDP.
Right, so this was free.
Free memory savings.
Wonderful, right?
And we look at the memory.
We've basically taken the parameters.
And anything that's an optimizer state, I've divided by n GPUs,
right.
Wonderful, wonderful, wonderful.
Now, can we do more?
Well ZeRO stage 2 is now going to say,
I'm going to split the gradients up.
And then I'm going to shard that as well.
Now, this is going to be trickier
because before I was relying on the fact
that I can compute the entire gradient,
now I can't even materialize the whole gradient.
So what do I do.
Well, this turns out to just be a systems trick.
As I sweep backwards through my network,
I don't need to compute the full gradient.
I can send out the gradients to the associated workers as I go.
So the key step here is now, instead of materializing
the gradient vector all at once, I'm
going to walk backwards through the compute graph.
And after computing a layer's gradients,
I'm going to immediately just reduce
that to send that to the right worker, right.
And once gradients aren't needed in the backwards graph,
just immediately free it.
Right, so you're now incrementally computing
and sending gradients as you go.
And as you can see, doing it incrementally or doing it
all at once, same thing, right?
So it doesn't really make a difference.
So now you can, at the end, once again all gather the parameters.
I've started the gradients in some sense
without incurring any additional costs, right.
OK, so the last and the most hairy thing-- and this always,
when I first learned about this, seemed like total magic--
is we've gotten something for free so far,
so let's keep pushing it.
I'm going to shard the parameters as well all the way
across all the states.
And so we're going to use the same kind of idea
that we used in ZeRO stage 2.
And the idea, remember, was I'm going to do things
incrementally, right.
And so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to send and receive parameters on demand while
stepping through the compute graph.
And this is really tricky, because each GPU only
sees a slice of both the parameters, gradients,
and optimizer states at any one time, right.
And this is ZeRO stage 3, also known as FSDP.
If you've ever parallelized anything in a Torch library,
you've probably dealt with this before.
So the way that it works under the hood
is what you're going to do is you're
going to do two all-gathers and one reduce-scatter as you go.
So we're going to step from left to right here.
And this is going to be the entire update process.
So what you do is you're going to load your model.
You have your two GPUs at the top and the bottom.
You're first going to gather your weights for this one layer.
I'm going to forward this one layer.
And then I can free my weights, because I've already done
the forward, right.
I don't need these parameters anymore.
Now, let's say I only have one layer.
Now I can move to the backwards process.
Now to do the backwards step, I need the activations,
which I've kept.
And I need the parameters for this layer, which
I can all-gather on demand.
I all-gather it, I do the backwards.
And then I scatter the gradients back right when I get them.
Right, so I got the gradients.
I reduce-scatter the gradients out.
And then I free the weights.
I don't need them anymore, and I repeat this process, right.
So I grab the parameters as I need them.
I compute my backwards.
I send the gradients out, and I repeat this process.
And then I update my weights.
All done, right.
So what's the communication cost?
Right, how many all-gathers did we do?
We did two all-gathers, one reduce-scatter.
Also, so we have one extra all-gather, which seems bad.
That's one thing.
The second thing is this seems a little crazy in terms
of the overhead, because we're doing communication
all the time.
Every layer, we're doing this communication.
You might think that this is extremely expensive and bad.
But I think one of the things that's
counterintuitive and important is
ZeRO stage 3 uses two really important ideas to make
this essentially overhead free.
So the first one, which we've already seen,
is this idea that we're going to sweep through the compute graph,
and then we're going to do the necessary communication
and then immediately free the memory.
Right, that's already an idea we've experienced.
The other idea, which I haven't talked about yet,
is we're going to overlap the communication and computation
cost of this process, right.
And this is hard to explain initially.
So I think I've taken this plot from this paper, which
I think was explaining the PyTorch FSDP architecture.
So the way that this works is in order-- so we have different
streams here.
This is what's happening in the CPU.
This is what's happening in the GPU for computation,
and then what's happening in the GPU for communication
at the very bottom here.
Now, the way FSDP works is I have to first get my parameters
before I can do my computation.
So I'm going to all-gather 0, layer 0, right.
And once I've all-gathered, I can now do my forward.
But as I'm doing my forward, notice
that I'm requesting the next layer's parameters.
I'm all gathering 1 while I'm doing this computation.
And now I all-gathered 1, I can now do forward 1, right.
And I can start all-gathering 2 while I'm starting this process.
And so I'm overlapping computation and communication
as I'm doing this.
And I might spend some time freeing my parameters.
I might also spend some time computing another forward.
For example, if you reuse that W nought,
I'm reusing this forward 0 twice.
And so what this allows you to do
is if you have enough computation and your network's
fast enough, by overlapping communication and computation,
right.
FSDP can basically be free.
Right, you do see some bubbles.
These are overheads.
But if your comms is very fast and your computation
is very big, right, you can easily
see how the computation can run faster than the communication--
I'm sorry, the computation can take
longer than the communication, and you
end up having this really great improvement in memory usage
without paying for almost any amount of memory use.
OK, so when we look at the different ZeRO stages,
right, DDP, the naive data parallel,
costs 2 times parameters.
Right, it was a single all-reduce.
The two ZeRO stages, 1 and 2, right,
the ones that shard gradient and optimizer state,
this is free in the literal sense,
because it has the same amount of communication cost, right.
It's just the identity of all-reduce
being equivalent to two operations, right.
Now, ZeRO stage 3 is technically a little bit more
communications.
You need an extra all-gather, right.
But it's not so bad because of the really clever ways
in which all these libraries can hide the communication cost
underneath the computation.
So in practice, FSDP, if you run it,
you're going to see GPU utilization that's
very close to just the single GPU performance.
It is actually quite remarkable how good FSDP is.
And it's also very conceptually simple.
You will actually have to write an FSDP implementation
as part of your assignment.
And you can just write a wrapper that will wrap any module
and turn it into its FSDP version.
Right, conceptually, all you're going to do
is do a bunch of all-gathers, compute, free, and then repeat
on the backwards pass.
OK, good.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes?
--gradients from the next GPU to calculate the gradients
for the previous GPU, right?
When you say-- so we're not--
I think what you just described, which
is taking gradients from one GPU to the next, that's
closer to pipelining.
Pipelining would be if one layer was on one GPU
and another layer was on another GPU.
That's not the case.
So in all these cases, every GPU goes through the entire model,
right, from the start to finish.
But the difference is, no GPU is going
to hold the entire parameters at the same time.
And so what we're going to do is if I only
have part of the network that doesn't have layer 0,
I'm going to demand the layer 0 parameters first
and then do the full computation.
And then I'll move on to the next layer, right.
So it's the same computation.
It's the same single GPU computation
as naive data parallel.
But you can just think of it as request parameters,
free parameters in between every computational operation.
Yes?
So are you saying that every GPU has a part of every layer,
and that's what the all-gather's for?
Yes, that's right.
So the picture is here, right.
Parameters, gradients, and optimizer states
are all sharded across the different GPUs.
That's right.
Yeah, good.
Oh, yes.
Why does the communication cost not
multiply by the number of layers as well?
So the number of operations multiplies by layer.
So that's correct.
But each of these communication pieces is smaller, right.
Because this is just one tiny MLP or something.
And I'm comparing that to the cost of all-reducing
a whole network.
Right, so it all adds up in some sense.
Yeah, good.
All right.
OK, good.
So in practice, if you look at the maximum size that can fit
on, let's say, a A100 GPU, if you go from the baseline,
you can not even fit a 7B model.
And you go to ZeRO stage 3.
You can now fit 50 billion parameter models and so on,
right.
So it becomes a lot easier to fit these big models using FSDP.
Right, the improvements that you get
in terms of the memory improvement
is quite significant.
OK, yes.
So can you go back to the previous slide?
So regarding this on 8x1 A100, what would be the limitation
on H100 or P200?
OK, I can't do the mental math of multiply by 141
and divide by 80, but that would be the number for an H200.
And so on and so forth.
Yeah, it would be linear, right.
It wouldn't really change the math very much,
though, to go from one accelerator to up.
OK, so FSDP, I think, is very clean.
It's very elegant.
I like it a lot.
I wish I could end the lecture here.
But unfortunately, we will have to proceed into uglier
and more hairy things.
And there's two reasons why we have to do that.
One of them, and this is an important idea
for parallelization, is that in some sense,
data parallel is consuming an important resource.
And that resource is the batch size, so to speak, right.
If you have a batch size of 8, you
can never have more than eight accelerators, right.
And you might think, OK, let's just make
the batch size bigger and bigger and bigger
as we have accelerators.
You can't do that, because at a certain point,
there's something called the critical batch size, where
the basically gain that you get from the additional batch
element is less than if you had taken another SGD step
on that single element, right.
So there comes a point where at small batch sizes,
adding extra elements is perfectly helpful.
It's the same as taking more SGD steps.
But at a certain point, diminishing return hits in.
An infinitely large batch size is not infinitely better
than infinite steps, right.
Infinite single steps.
Because of this, now we have faced a hard tradeoff.
Do we want small batch sizes and let our GPUs be more idle?
Do we want big batch sizes and take the hit from optimization?
Hard to say, rigt.
There's another issue that we have,
which is that we still have memory issues, which
is ZeRO stages 1 and 2 don't really
let you scale memory at all.
And ZeRO stage 2 lets you cut up the parameter memory.
But unfortunately, there's activation memory
and other kinds of memory use that this does not split up
or this does not reduce at all, right.
And so we need better ways, more fine grained ways,
of cutting up the model in order to really start
pushing down the memory use beyond these points, right.
And so this takes us to various model parallelism ideas.
And so model parallelism is going
to be this idea of essentially like FSDP,
we're going to split up the parameters across GPUs.
But I think the important conceptual difference
between what we talked about and what we will talk about next
is that now we are going to communicate activations.
Right, in FSDP, we cut up the parameters.
But in some sense, it was just a wrapper.
We were still doing the normal computation.
We were just sending parameters back and forth before doing it.
Right, so parameters were the things flying around.
Now what we're going to do instead
is we're going to communicate activations
back and forth, right.
So if, for example, one layer lives on GPU 0,
the next one lives on GPU 1.
Right, what I have to communicate
is the activation of the layer in between.
Right, so that's going to be the big difference.
And this will involve pipeline parallel, which is cutting up
layers, tensor parallel, which is cutting up matrices,
and expert parallel, which is sharding experts
into different places.
Right, and Percy's talked about tensor parallel already,
so you have roughly some mental model of this.
I'll start by talking about pipeline parallel or layer
wise parallel.
This is, I think, conceptually very simple.
Back in the days when I first learned about parallelism,
I was like, ah, yes, it's simple.
Just cut up the layers and put them on different GPUs.
Right, very simple thing.
And so you're going to pass activations forward
in the forward pass, and then you're
going to pass like partial gradients
backwards in the backward pass.
Now, OK, if I do this, what will happen?
You will get a terrible looking picture like this.
Very, very depressing.
I have four accelerators, each handling a quarter of the model.
And so what computation happens as a function of time.
So time is sweeping from left to right.
And the different accelerators are the different rows.
So first, my zeroth accelerator at the bottom here,
that's handling the first layer will do some computation.
And then it will stop, right.
And then it will hand off the computation to the second one.
And then it will do nothing for the rest of time
until the very end.
And then I will basically be passing things back and forth.
And one GPU will be active at a time.
And then coming backwards, one GPU
will be active handling the backward pass at a time.
And so most of the time, my GPUs are idle.
My utilization is truly, truly terrible.
And this is called a bubble.
It's the part of the pipeline where you're not doing anything.
And the solution to this is to essentially do
a batching or pipelining.
So instead of doing a simple one layer after another,
you're going to have a pipeline, right.
Where, in this case, in this picture here,
you have four elements to be processed.
And as soon as you process one, you start on the next element,
and then you pass off the one that's already
done to your next layer.
Right, so you can do this to essentially pass elements
upwards and then back downwards.
And so if you want to make this reasonable, then what you need
is the ratio of essentially this bubble
time to the useful compute.
The utilization, in some sense, is
going to be the number of stages divided by this micro-batches.
And so we need a huge batch size in order
to reduce this bubble towards 0.
Right, so if we want our bubble to be 0,
it's going to go down as 1 over the microbatch size.
This is why I said batch sizes are useful resource.
Because now we can spend it in a different way, which
is to pipeline more to reduce the amount of idle time
in pipeline parallel.
OK, so pipelines are terrible.
And by folklore, people say things
like, parallelization code looks reasonable
and people can understand it until you
implement pipeline parallel.
So why do we do pipeline parallel?
Well, pipelines can save memory compared to DDP.
Because we've cut up layers, and you can also compose
this with data parallel.
So you can do both.
But the other reason why this is a very important idea to learn,
and you will always have a pipeline in certain kinds
of topologies, is that it has very good communication
properties compared to both FSDP and compared to any other kinds
of things you can do.
It only depends on activations, like b times s times h.
It is also point to point.
One layer is going to communicate to another.
It's not all to all.
And so depending on how you sequence these things,
they can be a very efficient way to utilize your network.
So in practice, what we're going to do
is that pipelines are going to live on the slowest networking
links.
So if you have multiple data centers or multiple pods that
are slower to talk to, you're going
to parallelize across those two using pipelined parallel,
because that's the most communication
efficient parallelism that you can bring to bear here.
OK.
And as I said, pipeline performance
is really dependent on batch size.
So I'll point out this paper repeatedly,
but I'll mention which one this is.
Now this is the Megatron paper from NVIDIA.
They have a bunch of really lovely parameter sweeps of what
happens to utilization as a function
of different configurations you can do.
So if you have large batch sizes and you pick a large pipeline
size, you can get pretty good utilization
close to not doing pipeline parallel at all.
But you need the big batch sizes in order
to be able to keep utilization up.
Otherwise, pipeline parallel is going
to rapidly degrade your utilization and performance.
Actually, I'm going to pause for a moment
here to ask questions, because the next slide is complicated.
Yes?
So you mentioned on the previous slide
that pipelines have good communication properties,
like the FSPD.
What is the specific mechanism for why that is?
It's a smaller amount of stuff that's being communicated.
So it's batch times sequence length times hidden.
And that's almost always a smaller amount
of data than attempting to communicate a whole parameter
matrix, right.
So people have tried to figure out
much more clever ways of reducing
the amount of pipeline sizes.
And you can do clever things that
cut up the different stages of what
you're doing for different layers
or different micro-batches.
So you can sequence different forward pass elements
in between different backwards pass elements.
And by doing clever scheduling, you
can further reduce the bubble size.
This was taken from the DeepSeek paper.
So by really cleverly manipulating
when you're doing forward and backward computation,
you can get a little bit better in terms of the bubble size.
But I think the even more clever thing that you can do,
which is called zero bubble pipelining,
is not really about scheduling per se.
But it's actually about thinking carefully
about the structure of your backward pass.
So in the backward pass, there's really
two things that have to happen.
If you think about it, you're going backwards
in your computation graph.
And as you do that, you're going to do two things.
One is going to be you're going to propagate
your partial derivatives further down your computation graph.
So remember, back propagation, you start at the end,
and you're propagating these partial derivatives back, right.
So you have to do that.
But you also want to compute the gradients
for the current weight.
Right, so you have two things that you
do at every node of your computation graph.
You're going to propagate backwards,
and you're going to compute the derivative of your weight.
The important thing about thinking
about this compute graph is actually, one of these two
is really important for pipelines.
And the other one, you can do whenever.
Propagating the partials backwards,
right, that's very important.
Because your next stage can't do any work until you've propagated
that signal back.
On the other hand, the derivative
with respect to the weights, that
is a leaf node, so to speak, on this graph.
And I can do it whenever, right.
And so the clever thing to do now is you separate these two.
Right, so you got your B's over here.
These B's are the backwards, propagating backwards.
And then these W's, these W's are computing
the derivative of the weights.
And they can happen whenever.
So what you do is you compute the B's as quickly as you can.
Right, so those come first.
And then you can defer the W's until later
and do it when you have a gap in your computation.
And when you do this, you can basically almost all completely
fill up the pipeline.
And the zero bubble pipelining thing
is very complicated or much more complicated
than you would normally like to deal with.
But it allows you to almost deal with these pipelining issues
almost entirely, depending on essentially the workload
involved in the W versus the B, and so on and so forth.
But I think having seen this, I was like, oh, this is so clever.
Such clever things that you can do with systems.
OK, so that was pipelining.
Any questions about that?
Good.
So I think there's a natural analogy
or a parallel you can think of.
So pipeline parallel is like depth.
So your depth, you cut up your network
along the depth dimension.
But we have two ways that we scale, right.
We've got a depth axis and we have a width axis.
So what if we start cutting up our model along width, right?
So this is tensor parallel, as Percy explained before.
And it's really the simple idea that matrix multiplies
can be cut up into smaller matrix multiplies, which
you then add the partial sums back together.
This is really the same idea as tiling as well.
So this core primitive just appears many, many times.
And so when you do this in practice,
right, what does this actually look like?
So this is a GeLU that's happening.
So what do you normally do?
You have your x coming in as input on the very right
of this slide here.
And then I have a matrix A that I multiply with.
I apply my non-linearity GeLU.
And then I multiply with B to downproject.
And then I output my z.
Right, this is the normal serial computation that I do.
Now in tensor parallel, what I would do
is I would cut out my A into two submatrices, my B
into two submatrices, and then I would run the computations
in parallel, and I would gather them together at the end.
Now, one thing that is important is
there's a duality between the forward and backward pass.
So in the forward pass, all I do with the x is I copy them twice,
and then I run the computation forward.
So f is the identity, this f function.
And then once I get to the end of my parallel component,
the g function, that's an all-reduce that brings them
back together, right.
But in the backwards pass, as I'm doing my gradients,
this is going to flip.
My g is going to be on-- sorry, my g is going to be an identity.
Right, because the partial derivatives
are coming backwards.
And then my f are the partials that I
need to sum up in order to get my partial derivatives
at the start of this module.
Right, so they're going to flip.
And this duality is important if you're
going to write tensor parallel.
OK.
And so you might have already noticed, right.
But when we split things, some of the ways
that we are going to be column-wise.
So column-wise, tensor parallel is
going to happen at the inputs.
Right, so the inputs of the MLP, the projections of the attention
are going to be cut up by the columns in each transformer
block.
So this is column-wise cuts.
And then there's going to be row-wise cuts
in the corresponding second stage.
So in the downprojections of the MLP,
as well as the outputs of the attention,
you're going to have a row-wise cut.
And then everything that's a small layer, like a layer
norm or a non-linearity or routers in ML--
sorry, in MoEs, those are all fully replicated
across the machines.
You don't really want to bother with the overhead of cutting
those guys.
OK.
And then, so when do we do tensor parallel?
Tensor parallel is extremely computation hungry.
What you're doing is every time you have a matmul,
you're going to be doing some communication.
Right, you have an all-reduce.
Or in the backwards pass, you have all-reduce here.
One in the G when you're going forward.
And these are activation size, and you're
doing them very frequently.
So this is very communication hungry.
And so you only want to do this within a node.
So for GPUs, GPUs are going to be networked tightly together
in a single box.
And so up to eight, you might be willing to do some tensor
parallel.
Once you go beyond that, you're going to be going cross node.
And those interconnects, those connections, are much slower.
And so you're going to get a big drop in performance
as soon as you hit that point of going beyond a single machine.
So tensor parallel, you should remember as very communication
hungry.
You usually use it in the fastest interconnects
that you have at hand.
And this is the point at which I'm
going to go back to the thing I said about TPUs.
Right, remember for TPUs, you don't really
have this distinction between fast eight GPUs
and next machines.
You just have this big mesh.
And so one of the big advantages that TPU people will
tell you is you can tensor parallel very large numbers
compared to the GPU world, because they're
able to have high bandwidth in this very regular communication
pattern over this mesh.
Right, so that's a big difference
if you're parallelizing between TPUs versus GPUs.
The amount of tensor parallelism you use versus pipeline parallel
will actually be quite different.
So how do we compare these two.
They're both model splitting strategies.
They'll both save on both parameters
and potentially activations.
The pros here of tensor parallel is that there's
no necessarily pipeline bubble.
And if your network's fast enough,
you might be able to get full utilization.
It's also low complexity.
It's just cutting up some matmuls.
But the con is that the communication is much larger.
It used to be that you were doing b times s times h
point to point communication.
Now instead, I'm going to be doing something like a times
b times s times h times roughly one all-reduce communication,
right.
So this is not even just point to point.
This is all to all communication that needs to happen.
So tensor parallel is great.
Whenever we have high speed interconnects, every other time,
we probably want to be using pipeline parallel.
OK.
So the last thing I want to talk about about--
we're talking about memory use, is to really think
more carefully about memory.
I think the most naive view of memory in deep learning
and language modeling is something like, well, memory
is just parameters.
That's this green bit over here.
Right, you have a certain number of bits you need
to store for your parameters.
That's it.
I've already talked about optimizer state,
which is important, which is this yellow box over here.
But if you look at this plot, this
is actual memory use as profiled in one of the PyTorch profilers.
You'll find actually that this is not really the whole story.
There's a lot of dynamic memory that needs
to exist in a computation.
You need to store all the activations.
These are these big red bumps over here.
And then as you compute your gradients,
you need to store them in your backward sweep, right.
And so really maximum memory usage
happens a little bit after the maximum activation point.
After you start sweeping backwards on your gradient,
but you still need to compute a lot-- keep your activations,
those are usually the maximum memory points, right.
So to reduce this, maybe we need to deal with this big red hump,
this activation.
And if you start looking at more modern workloads for language
models, you start to find that as you
get to bigger and bigger parameters--
forget the column that says present work.
I'll talk about that in a moment here.
But if you look at just the baseline columns of this plot,
as you go to bigger models, for moderately large sequence
lengths, your activations are just
going to dwarf the parameter memory that you need.
And so any memory saving strategy
has to reason about activations in order to be fully effective.
We can't just deal with parameter memory.
That's not really sufficient for us.
So if we're storing everything-- and this is a good,
I don't know, statistic or rule of thumb to start with.
If we need to store everything, the amount
of activations that we need is going
to be something like 34 times s times b times h,
and that's going to be sequence length times batch
size times hidden dimension size plus 5 times as over h.
as is attention heads times sequence length divided
by hidden dimension size.
And this sbh dependence, right, is fundamental,
because we expect to have to store something
for every element of the sequence.
We expect to have to store something for every batch
element, and we expect to have to store something
for every hidden dim size.
Right, so we're going to see this sbh term repeatedly
as we try to go through different ways of reducing
activation memory and accounting for the total amount
of activation memory.
And in case you're curious where the terms come from,
this odd looking term, the 5 as over h
is going to come from the quadratic attention terms,
including the dropout terms.
And we can drop this term via recomputation
if we do flash attention.
OK.
Now what if we did tensor parallel?
One of the promises that I made to you
in talking about model parallelism
was that we could reduce activation quite a bit.
So now let's think about what happens.
Well, tensor parallel is going to split out
the matrix multiplies in attention and MLPs.
So which parts are those?
Well, the MLPs are 24 of those 34 that I talked about before.
And the attention heads are 5 as over ht.
Right, the second term over here.
Now, I can reduce that by t, my tensor parallel size.
And that's good.
This is not bad.
Because I've taken most of the memory,
and I've made it scale linearly with the tensor parallel size t.
So that's good.
But it turns out that there are other things that you do.
You might have a layer norm.
You might have a dropout.
You need to keep the inputs to attention and the MLP.
Right, because the inputs to each layers
need to be stored as residuals for the backwards pass.
And unfortunately, these are not reduced
with your tensor parallel size.
Right, tensor parallel does not split the layer norm.
And therefore, it does not split the activation for these guys.
So this is unfortunate, because you were hoping that if you had
1,000 different GPUs in tensor parallel because you're Google,
you might be able to reduce this activation dramatically.
The unfortunate reality is that you're still
going to suffer a 10 times sbh penalty for doing all of this.
And so the last part that's usually
used in composition with tensor parallel
is this idea of sequence parallel.
This is an extremely misleading name,
because usually when I say sequence parallel, actually
there's a thing called context parallel that is actually
more natural for this name.
But sequence parallel is the following idea.
So what you're going to do is we have
these remaining terms, 10 sbh.
And these terms are very lightweight.
They're like layer norms.
They're stuff that doesn't have much computation.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to split them up somehow.
And I'm going to split them up over the sequence axis
rather than over the hidden axis.
And this is going to then involve
all-gathers and reduce-scatters before every operation where
we need these.
And if you think about it, this is very reminiscent of FSDP.
Right, we have this thing that we need.
We need attention-- sorry, we need activations at some point.
We need to compute the activations going forward,
and we need the activations when we sweep backwards
for the derivatives, right.
But we don't need them now.
So we're going to store them by splitting them up
across the sequence axis and materializing them on demand.
So I would say this is conceptually very
similar to the FSDP style idea, where we're storing them
in this sharded format, and then we're
gathering them as we need them.
And then as I said before, there's a duality to this.
So in the forward pass, g is an all-gather. g
bar is a reduce-scatter.
In the backwards pass, this is going to be reversed.
Right, the all-gather and reduce-scatter
are going to be reversed between g and g bar.
So if I do this now, what do I get?
Well, remember, with the no parallelism setting,
the very first part, what I told you was you get this activation
memory.
Use 34 times sbh with an attention head component.
With tensor parallel, I get to divide the MLP
part and the attention part by t,
but not all these other pointwise ops that I have.
If I do sequence parallel, I've split these
up by my accelerators as well, just
in the sequence axis, which gives me
now fully linear dependence.
If I do activation recomputation,
I can even drop this second term.
Because remember, this is just the storage
that I need for the softmax.
So I can drop this through recomputation, which
gives you sbh times 34 over t.
This is nice to remember, because this
is the lower bound of what you can achieve,
reasonably speaking, for normal training for activation memory.
And so if you want to do things like compute
by hand whether your model will fit into a GPU,
this is a good thing to remember.
You need at least this much for activation memory.
You're going to need some memory for your optimizer state,
and you will need some memory for your parameters
and your gradient.
And once you have those things, you
have a rough sense of how much memory
you're going to need for your model.
OK, I'm going to stop here for a moment.
I have talked through both pipeline and tensor
parallel at this point, and so people might be a little bit
confused.
And we can talk through a few things
before I move on to expert parallel.
Good.
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, yes?
24 over t is the MLP part.
The MLP part cannot be optimized through the representation?
You can recompute the MLP as well.
You can do a lot more computation
than what is listed here.
But recomputation what is listed here
is very computationally expensive,
like a recomputation for MLP involves running the MLP again
in the backward pass, which you probably do not want to do.
Recomputation for attention is generally cheaper, yeah.
Because you do it time-wise as well.
And also you don't want to pay the quadratic cost.
That's quite expensive.
The quadratic cost.
That's quite painful, yeah.
Cool, all right.
So I'm going to now talk about the last ingredient
in the standard parallelism toolbox, which
is expert parallelism, right.
Now that MoEs are very standard part of the toolkit,
most big models are MoEs these days.
And that allows us to take advantage
of one of their big benefits, which is expert parallelism.
And expert parallelism, I think of myself
as being something analogous to tensor parallel.
Right, in the sense that you're taking the MLPs,
right, the FFN components of your network.
And you're going to split them up in various ways,
and you'll incur a communication penalty in the same way
that you're maybe splitting up the matrices,
except here you're splitting up the MLP
across different devices.
And the systems behavior of tensor parallel is--
oh, sorry, expert parallel-- is roughly like tensor parallel
as well in the sense that this is a high bandwidth parallelism
primitive that also reduces activation.
But one important thing is that if you're doing an MoE,
you almost always prefer using an expert parallel sharding
strategy over tensor parallel.
And I've taken this screenshot from the parallelism guidelines
from Megatron, which is NVIDIA's like parallelism library.
It's a really wonderful library and document.
And one of the guidelines, they say is,
look, if you're going to do some of parallelism,
either EP or TP, you should be using EP over RP.
Why is that?
Well, this is actually a good list
of drawbacks for tensor parallel.
If you have a matrix and then you cut up the matrix too
finely, well, the matrices are going to start to get small
and your GPU utilization will suffer.
So you want your matmuls as big as possible,
and tensor parallel reduces that.
For MoE layers, it's a lot easier
to route sparse token activations
rather than to potentially route these dense big tensor parallel
matmul activations.
And then you can do things like route tokens exactly
to the places that they need.
And you can skip some computation-- or sorry,
some overhead in the cases that if you're
going to have MoE anyway, you might
as well have the number of experts split up
over all the devices.
Now, this-- sorry, yeah.
This might make it seem like, all right, EP is great.
Everyone should be doing expert apparel all the time.
Unfortunately, expert parallel is still
really complicated and still very difficult.
I think everything that I've said after FSDP--
tensor parallel, pipeline parallel, systems wise
is quite non-trivial to get working really well.
And I'll just point to two different libraries
not to tell you the details of what happens inside of them,
but to tell you, this is seriously complicated business.
DeepSeek has a library called DPP,
which I think is one of my favorite things
from the DeepSeek V3 era, which is basically
their own library for doing expert parallel routing
and dispatching, where they're looking at really low level GPU
networking primitives in order to try to basically combine
different operations or have the hardware handle
certain operations in order to make MoE routing
as efficient as possible.
Similarly, NVIDIA has a library called Hybrid EP, which
is a similar effort of having very efficient low level
hardware implementations of expert parallel dispatching.
And just to give you the high level thing,
right, the reason why this stuff is hard
is you are doing a lot of all to all dispatching.
If you look at the communications pattern of MoE,
much like tensor parallel, every time you have a MLP,
you're going to have to route tokens
all sorts of different places, and you
need to do this in a very latency sensitive way.
Because your computation is waiting for your tokens
to arrive.
So reducing the latency of this dispatch
is extremely, extremely important.
And one final thing that is like a fun trivia about the DPP
library is the deep sea cloaks are
so intense that in order to optimize,
like every last bit of performance,
they basically looked and found undocumented ptx, which
is like GPU machine code or machine code like things.
And they found how to use these undocumented instructions
to further accelerate their networking communication.
So really, this is the level of stuff
that you need in order to get to the frontier of parallelism
efficiency.
Finally, up until now, I've talked about all the parallelism
primitives in isolation, like data parallel
and so on and so forth.
With the implicit assumption that you can just put
them together like LEGO blocks.
And this is true, for the most part,
for basically all the other parallelism strategies.
It's very easy to combine, I don't know,
data and tensor parallel.
Expert parallel has additional constraints
that you want to be somewhat respectful of.
Usually, the naive way to do data and expert
parallelism, which I think is in many of the old libraries,
is that the replicas for DP and EP are the same.
So in other words, let's say I have
a data parallelism of eight.
I'm going to shard my experts across those eight replicas.
And then my data will be split across those eight replicas
and routed in various ways.
Right, so in other words, you split your GPUs according to DP,
and then your EP is a subset of that split.
Right, and this is a very natural thing
to do because you're routing tokens.
But if you do this, there's a maximum
bound to how far you can parallelize with EP.
And it constrains how DP and EP
And so I think this is the final complexity.
I apologize that expert parallel is a little bit
really messy in many ways.
But because of these complexities,
there is actually this one interesting systems thing
that I'll tell you about before I stop talking about EP,
which is this following fact.
Remember, MoEs only change the MLPs, right.
They don't change the attention at all.
Right, so because we're cutting up
the MLPs, but not the attention, this
means that expert parallelism kind of applies unevenly
to the model.
So when I parallelize at the expert level,
I'm parallelizing the MLPs, but I'm not parallelizing
the attention, right.
And so in order to parallelize the attention,
maybe I want to also use tensor parallel, right.
So I want a high tensor parallel level in order
to cut out my attention.
But this is going to then affect my MLPs.
Because if I have high tensor parallel and high expert
parallel, I've cut out my matrices
into really tiny pieces, and my utilization is very bad.
So there's this weird tradeoff where you want high tensor
parallel for the attention, but you want low tensor parallel
for the MLPs.
So there's this conflict.
So what do you do?
Well, in the last few years, people
have come up with more complicated system solutions
that decouple the tensor parallel
in the MLPs and the attention.
And so the attention layers get one kind of tensor parallel,
and the MoE layers get another kind of tensor parallel.
And so now you can fully decouple the parallelism.
And this leads to more complicated but more effective
combinations of EP and tensor parallel,
as well as data parallel.
Cool.
OK.
So the last thing in this space that I want to end with
is context parallel.
So context parallel or ring attention
is an idea of basically splitting activations
in a very long sequence across different accelerators.
And you can do things like pass the activations
to the device that's needed in this ring-like way following
the mesh topology of TPUs.
And so ring attention, which I think
was the original paper that did this,
showed that this worked really well on TPUs.
Context parallel is a standard parallelization strategy
that does this.
Both of these are used in long context extension stages
and in model serving.
I'm not going to talk about it, mainly because I think
it overlaps in concept to a lot of what
we've talked about already.
OK.
So this is the end of the second part.
And I think to put everything together,
I've made a big table of parallelization strategies,
including data parallel, which are the top two
rows and the various model parallelism strategies
below them.
And I think I've colored in red what I subjectively
feel like are the drawbacks of the different methods.
And the reason why I've colored things in red
is to try to convey to you that there
is no one strictly dominant parallelization strategy.
It's all a whole bunch of tradeoffs
that you somehow have to manage gracefully
in order to get a good outcome.
So for example, FSDP is great.
It's a wonderful strategy.
Does not help you with activation.
It consumes your global batch size
in order to do parallelization.
So it has limits.
And to address these, maybe you want
to compose them with some of these other tricks
that you have at hand.
Maybe you want to do some tensor parallel to cut down
on activation memory.
It also doesn't touch global batch size.
But if you do this, now you need fast networking
and you need high bandwidth.
And also then to leverage your slower connections, maybe
you want to use some of the other parallelization
strategies.
Right, so you see how all of these different advantages
means that there's a place for one of these parallelization
strategies in not every architecture,
but in many large scale architectures,
you use a large combination of these.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes?
Are they still applicable to MoEs, or is that strictly--
Yeah.
So the question was, is pipeline and, what,
FSDP applicable to MoEs?
Yes, yes, they're absolutely applicable.
If anything, the standard recommendation
is expert parallel is like tensor parallel.
So you want to go up to 8 or fast connections.
People don't really follow that anymore.
But even then, FSDP or data parallel in general and pipeline
and tensor are used extensively in all the frontier models.
Yeah.
Good.
OK, and you will do this or something like this
as part of your assignment.
But one of the things that's cool about parallelism
and I think is nice is that you can do some math, right.
You can actually say, OK, how much
compute do I do per layer for my different sharding strategies?
How much communication do I do per layer
for my different communication strategies?
And if I have different devices allocated
to different communication strategies,
how do these things scale?
And then I can figure out for a combination of these strategies,
how do they scale?
And you can start to make plots of,
if I have a certain batch size and I
have a certain parallelization strategy-- so I
have three different parallelization strategies here.
How much am I utilizing my GPU?
The ratio of compute time to communications time.
And as long as my compute time is longer than communications
time, in principle, you can just hide communications
underneath your computation.
And so you can make plots like this where this dashed line
at the very top, that's the boundary of where
you're efficient.
Anything above that is fully utilizing your computation.
Anything below that is on the bad part of your roofline.
You're waiting for communication to do your computation.
One thing that's pretty interesting here, right.
So I think this should feel intuitive to you
based on what I've told you.
If your batch size is big enough, FSDP only is good.
Right, if you have a batch size of 2,000, right, per chip,
then you how far can you go?
Well, you've got FSDP doing extremely well.
You're fully compute bound, right.
But the important thing is, as the batch size goes down,
FSDP only will hit a point where you're now communication bound.
Now, what do you do, right?
Well, what do you do is now, in order
to keep pushing efficiencies, you
have to incorporate MP, in this case,
is tensor parallel, to the mix.
Right, now you can push that curve out a little bit more
and be compute bound even into smaller batch size regimes,
right.
And you keep adding strategies to push this curve out in order
to get something better.
And this is what people call 3D or 4D--
I don't think there's 5D--
parallelism.
Which is when you put all these strategies together
to keep your compute units fully utilized
under different communication topologies.
There's a very simple prescription.
I think up until now, I've been telling you
things in generalities.
So it might feel complicated.
But I think actually the strategy for how you parallelize
is very simple, actually.
Which is, until your model fits into memory,
you're going to cut up your model by whatever
means necessary, right.
And how are you going to cut up your model.
You're going to use either tensor or expert parallel
for your fast interconnect.
And so if you have eight GPUs per machine,
you're going to use a tensor expert parallel of eight.
And then you're going to pipeline parallel or Zero-3,
which is FSDP, the rest of the way to make your model fit.
And once your model fits, then you're
going to just data parallel the rest of the way.
Right, then use up the rest of your GPUs with data parallel,
right.
If your batch size ends up being too small,
you can do gradient accumulation to get better GPU utilization.
Very simple strategy.
And this is borne out in the actual large scale
parallel training libraries that you might use.
So I've added the link here to Megatron's guide
to parallelizing MoEs.
But this idea actually applies to the dense models as well.
And you see exactly the thing that I
said, but in reverse order.
So guideline number one is minimize model parallelism,
maximize data parallelism.
Right, so use most of your GPUs to shard data if you can.
Now, if you're using GPUs, stay within NVLink.
So that's one machine, or so one box, right.
Keep expert parallel and tensor parallel within one box.
And then if you're going to go multi-node,
use pipeline parallelism to go multi-node.
And then if you're MoE, then prefer expert parallel.
And then finally, if you're doing long sequences,
use context parallel.
Right, ring attention.
So exactly what I've been trying to get across
to you through the lecture, but in practitioner
form that you see here.
OK, the final component-- actually,
maybe I can pause here, in case anyone's curious about 4D
parallelization stuff.
Yeah.
I know you said context parallel would
be a better name for decreasing parallel [INAUDIBLE]
Oh, yeah, yeah.
Well, I mean, sequence parallel is often
just you do it with tensor parallel
in order to reduce activations.
It's more of an add on that you put in
in order to reduce activation.
It's not its own standalone thing, in many cases.
Yeah?
With the suspicions that this is like a loop transformer,
like that, does that make things easier or harder?
OK.
I don't how much I buy the loop transformer mythos rumors.
Maybe it is.
It would be interesting.
But to the question of how the systems structures would change,
it's a good question.
I mean, I guess it might mess with things like FSDP.
You can't really discard the weights.
It does have the advantage, though,
that you don't have to keep getting weights.
It is much more parameter efficient,
and so maybe much of the model parallelism stuff
wouldn't be as important.
It would be interesting.
It would be definitely different for a lot of the FSDP style
things.
Because the FSDP strategy is really predicated on getweights,
discard weights, getweights, discard weights.
And in a loop, you're not discarding anything.
Good, OK.
All right.
So this is an old paper, but it is actually probably one
of the best resources.
And also, it's not like the networking fundamentals
changed that much.
So I think the lessons from here are very relevant today.
And so this is a paper by NVIDIA and formerly
unfortunately, Stanford folks, Matei and Deepak,
who did a bunch of runs of large scale parallel
training across many different configurations
to basically tell you, as you're scaling up,
how should your parallelization strategies
change across different scales?
And you see exactly this prescription
that I've been talking about before, which is, you
have data parallel maxed out.
And then your tensor parallel increases until it hits 8,
and then you stop because you don't want to go any higher.
And then from that point on, your pipeline parallel increases
and increases and increases, right.
And with sufficiently large scale, data parallel decreases.
And at the very end, you have a DP of six.
And this is because you just need this much tensor
and pipeline parallel to fit the stuff.
Right, and you're using the rest of your budget on data parallel.
And if you put them all together,
right, even as you go to ludicrously large numbers
of GPUs, your utilization stays very flat and very good.
And this is why I think you see this gigantic data center
build-outs.
The parallelization strategies people have come up with
are so effective.
And the hardware for communication
is so good that even with the gigantic data centers or even
cross data center training, you can get really good utilization
across these different regimes.
They have really nice quantitative evidence
showing you, for different batch sizes for tensor parallel, what
is the right place to stop?
And it's clearly tensor parallel size of 8.
As you go beyond that, you're going to get into trouble.
And pipeline parallel, you also need big batch sizes
in order to be able to utilize the machines effectively.
That's why there's a blue to orange gap.
There's pipeline parallel.
And the larger the pipeline parallel, the larger the gap
between orange and blue.
And then I think another thing that maybe you have already
internalized from flash attention but maybe not is maybe
you should do a bunch of activation recomputation.
Because if you do activation recomputation very cleverly,
then you can get a bigger batch size,
and the bigger batch size then allows
you to get better utilization.
This is a, initially, I think, very counterintuitive
observation that actually you should
do more computation via recomputation
in order to end up getting better utilization,
because it allows you to save memory,
and memory can be turned into batch size.
OK.
So that was a more quantitative view
of how to pick parallelism strategies.
The last thing I want to end with
is just to look at just a very few training runs.
And looking at the training runs, maybe
we can get a sense of how modern parallelization is
used in practice and how it's evolving.
So Dolma by AI2 was a seven be open source model.
Sorry, Olmo, which was trained on the Dolma data set.
And this isn't the Dolma paper for the details.
Was a 7B model trained fully with FSDP across a whole bunch
of accelerators.
I forget exactly how many.
But this is one example of FSDP scales
surprisingly well, even to many, many GPUs.
As long as you're training a small model,
FSDP is actually a pretty good strategy for parallelization.
I think many 7D-ish models are trained purely with FSDP.
DeepSeek, because of their systems skills,
does do some pretty exotic and useful stuff.
So DeepSeek V1 was trained just with data
parallel ZeRO stage 1 with tensor sequence and pipeline
parallel, as I talked to you before.
DeepSeek V3, that's a MoE model, if you remember my MoE lecture.
So they have not only pipeline parallel,
but they also have expert parallel instead
of tensor parallel, right.
And their expert parallel actually is a little bit exotic.
Because they have 64 way parallelism.
So they group eight different machines together, and that's
their expert parallel domain.
And to enable this large expert parallel,
they basically use the same tricks
that they have from their pipeline parallel
pipelining in order to try to make sure
that expert parallel doesn't have low utilization periods.
So this is actually quite a complicated trick
that they do to get these very large expert parallel splits.
Another example, Yi, from Chinese open weights training
setting.
They use, once again, ZeRO stage 1 and tensor and pipeline
parallel.
Right, this very much makes sense.
It's the classic data parallel, tensor parallel,
pipeline parallel combo.
And once again, once you go to MoEs,
you replace the tensor parallelism
with expert parallelism.
Right, they serve similar goals.
But expert parallelism is just a little bit more efficient.
On the other extreme of a really big dense model,
you have Llama3.
The Llama3 report, I liked quite a bit,
because they're one of the few reports that
have literally a full breakdown of their parallelism strategy.
Not just like in the abstract, but across all
the different phases.
So the cool thing that you see is
they have a pre pre-training stage, a little warm-up
phase at the very start.
You can ignore that first row.
And then they have their main pre-training phase
in the middle row here.
And this is a very standard parallelization strategy.
Tensor parallel of 8, one context parallel, 16 pipeline
parallel, and 128 data parallel.
Big data parallel splits.
And then at the very end, because they want a long context
model, they do long context extension.
And for this, they crank up the context parallel,
lower the data parallel.
And that's how they parallelize this very memory hungry stage
for long context extension.
And notice, we're in tensor parallel,
not export parallel land.
Because Llama3 405B is a gigantic dense model.
It's not a MoE model.
And as a side note, right, one thing that I don't talk about,
but if you, for example, become an infra engineer at one
of these companies, you'll notice
is GPUs fail all the time.
Apparently during Llama3 405B training, GPUs failed 148 times.
And so you need lots of not just fast parallelism,
you need redundancy in order to be
able to deal with all these kind of horrible things
that can happen to your training.
So there's a distributed systems challenge as well.
Gamma 2, which is a Google open source model,
has FSDP plus tensor parallel and sequence parallel
and uses these two strategies only.
And the reason why I brought up Gamma 2
is, as far as I understand, this is basically a realization
of the Google claim that for TPUs, really
you don't need to do pipelines.
You just take a really big toroidal mesh
and you tensor parallel over that big mesh network
that you have.
Unclear whether this can scale out forever.
That has always been a little bit less clear to me.
But at least the gamma scales, this is definitely the case.
Finally, I took a look at some of the models that were trained
this year, like Mistral 8x22B, and during my investigation,
one of the things that I discovered was actually
if you're interested in model training and parallelism
configurations in the wild, NVIDIA has a repository called
Megatron Bridge, where they release a lot of recommended
training configurations for a lot of different model sizes
and model settings.
And you can take a look at what they end up saying is the right
model configuration for an 8x22B MoE or DeepSeek V3 modeling.
And so for Mixtral, they do expert parallel of 8,
pipeline parallel of 4, and an additional tensor parallel of 4.
This one for the attention layers.
And you see this follows the prescription
of, keep your expert parallel roughly around eight.
Nemotron 3 Super follows the DeepSeek V3 model,
has a bunch of expert parallel as well as context parallel,
because they were doing extensions,
at least in this article.
And then the last one that I want to talk about
is Qwen 3, which follows the DeepSeek
recipe, which is a fairly large amount of expert parallel 32.
And they have eight pipeline parallel and two tensor parallel
to split up things like the attention matrices.
It is actually interesting to see additionally
the different kinds of benchmarking
that NVIDIA folks have done for parallelizing different models.
And you see, I won't go into details of what this is.
This is in the NVIDIA bridge repo,
if you want to take a look.
There's all sorts of different configurations
that you can pick even within tensor parallel that
can significantly affect the performance of these.
So the systems integration is quite significant.
So to put everything together, I decided maybe
I would build an overview.
Really, the thing that's common to this is as much as you can,
all the models use data parallel.
They maximize the data parallel domains to the extent
that they can.
Tensor parallel almost always remains below eight.
And expert parallel can sometimes be big now.
And I think that's partially because of DeepSeek V3 and a lot
of the infra that they built for large scale expert parallel
training.
Good.
OK.
So to put everything together, right.
The highest level point, right, of this lecture
is we need to think about multi-GPU,
multi-node, maybe even multi-data center parallelism.
And to think about efficiency in that regime,
we need to really bring to bear all the approaches that we have.
Because you've got fast links, you've got slow links,
you've got techniques that make use of batch sizes and all
these different resources that you all want
to consume as much as possible.
But given all of these, it turns out
that there's fairly simple rules of thumb
for combining all these different forms of parallelism
to get in the end what is effectively
full utilization of your compute hardware.
Great.
And next week, I think we're talking about scaling laws.