OK.
Let's get started.
So welcome back, everyone.
So today we're going to talk about parallelism.
And remember in the last week, we
introduced how to make a single GPU go fast by writing kernels.
And we really looked inside this GPU.
And this week, we're going to talk
about how to leverage multiple GPUs to make
your code go even faster.
So the picture you should have in your head
is something like this.
So for the last week, we focused on one of these boxes,
where you have your GPU.
Remember, you have your High Bandwidth Memory, HBM, L2 cache,
L1 cache, registers, and a bunch of streaming multiprocessors.
So now the picture gets extended,
because instead of having one GPU, you might have four,
you might have 1,000 GPUs.
And those are going to be connected.
And I'll talk later about how those GPUs are
going to get connected.
And then you're going to have to figure out
how to leverage all of this compute to train models.
So in both cases, meaning both in the single GPU case
and in the multi-GPU case, as we'll talk about today,
the situation is kind of similar if you zoom out,
which is that the compute, the arithmetic logic units,
the tensor core, and so on, is far away from your data.
And far away for a single GPU means all the way
over here in HBM.
And now if you have multi GPUs, the thing that you need here
might be all the way on a different GPU,
and you're going to have to shuffle that over somehow.
But the same principles are going
to be the same, because the game is
to orchestrate the computation to try to avoid data transfer
bottlenecks.
It's very easy to use a ton of GPUs,
but it's hard to use them effectively.
So taking a little bit of liberty,
we can think about the generalized hierarchy
where at the local level next to the SMs
a single node single GPU where you have an L1 cache
shared memory.
This was the fastest.
And then you had HBM, which we lamented was so slow.
But in this lecture, HBM is going to be considered fast.
Now we're going to think about the single node multi-GPU
setting where the GPUs are going to be connected
via NVLink and NVSwitch.
And then finally, the multi-node and multi-GPU,
where we have to resort to InfiniBand
and ethernet depending on what network you have.
So last week, we talked about various tricks
for in reducing memory accesses, fusion and tiling.
Read into shared memory, do as much as you can,
and then write it back out.
And this week, we're going to talk
about how you can reduce the amount of communication
across GPUs by replicating and sharding appropriately.
So why do you do multi-GPUs?
The obvious answer is, well, you want to scale.
But to put a finer point on it, there's really two reasons.
One is that your parameters or activations or gradients
and optimizer state don't fit on the HBM memory of a single GPU.
So B21 has 192 gigabytes.
If you're training a 1 trillion parameter model,
that's not going to fit on a single GPU.
And the other reason is that even if your model could
fit on a single GPU, you might want
to leverage more GPUs by splitting everything up
to train faster.
So sometimes there will be some decisions
to be made because you could fit everything on GPUs,
but you have fewer cores.
But if you spread it out, then you're
going to have to pay the communication bandwidth.
So that's some calculation you're
going to have to do to figure out how to parallelize.
So just one note here is that so far this lecture is Python.
You execute it and you can just show everything.
Now, in this lecture, if you run this directly,
it uses multiprocessing.
But when I trace through it, I'm putting in some
of special single process mode.
So if you want to see the standard out
for this lecture run in the multiprocessing setup,
you can click here.
And I'll show this as we go through the lecture.
But just remember as we step through this lecture,
we're not actually doing multiprocessing,
because we're just stepping through single lines of code.
So this lecture is going to include two parts.
One is we're going to learn about the building
blocks of distributed communication and computation,
starting with the programming model.
Talk a little bit about the hardware.
Start to implement things in Torch,
which you're going to do on your assignment two.
And then the second part is we're going
to look at actual training.
We're going to look at three types of parallelism.
Data parallelism, tensor parallelism,
pipeline parallelism.
Each is going to cut up our model in different ways.
We're going to do this for MLPs rather than
the full transformer.
But it's really the core computation
is going to be shown here.
So let's dive in.
So the first thing to talk about is these things
called collective operations.
So collective operations are these primitives from
distributed programming that go back to the '80s.
So the idea of parallel programming is very old.
It wasn't invented for LLM training.
And it's still the case that these primitives
are the ones that we use today.
And here, collective just means that you're
specifying a general communication
pattern or a template across multiple devices,
rather than managing point to point how
this GPU is going to communicate with another GPU.
And this is going to be much easier,
and the system can do a lot more work for you.
So this is a very tried and trued interface
for doing parallel programming.
So the general setup is as follows.
The terminology here is a little bit--
I find it a little bit strange, but this is standard
in parallel programming.
The idea is that you have a bunch of ranks
where rank corresponds to a particular device, in our case
a GPU.
It could be a TPU.
But the point is that you have, let's say, four ranks here.
The world size corresponds to the number of devices,
so the world size here is four.
So there is a few operations we're going to go through.
Broadcast, scatter, gather, reduce,
all gather, reduce scatter, all reduce, and all to all.
And each of these operations is going
to specify how this set of ranks or devices
is going to transfer some amount of data
slash compute with it to some other set of devices.
So the first three, broadcast, scatter, gather, reduce,
are really just warm ups, I would say.
They allow you to get a sense of how these collective operations
work, but they're not really going
to be the ones that are driving most of training.
All gather, reduce scatter, and all
reduce are the ones that are going
to show up again and again for distributed training of language
models.
And finally, all to all I'll just
mention here, which is important for MOEs,
but we're not going to actually spend too much time
on this this lecture.
OK, so let's dive in with the simplest operation, which
is broadcast.
So in broadcasting, you have a rank 0.
It could be any rank, but let's just say for sake of picking
one, rank 0, has some tensor 0123.
And it broadcasts it to all the ranks.
So at the end of this operation, we have that each of the ranks
has the same tensor on it.
That should be pretty straightforward.
And this, again, doesn't really show up
in the core path of training.
Generally, broadcasts are used for initialization,
where let's say you initialize a load initial checkpoint
and then you broadcast it to all the ranks.
So something that's done like once.
So the second operation is a scatter.
And a scatter basically says, I have a tensor at rank 0
who is split up into the world size.
And I'm going to basically scatter
my tensor onto the other ranks.
So rank 0 gets 0, the zeroth component.
Rank 1 gets this, rank 2 gets this, and rank 3 gets that.
So again, this is not directly used,
but scatter is an important stepping stone
to understand reduced scatter.
So, as the name implies, scatter just takes a big tensor
at one place and spreads it out onto multiple places.
And you can see how this might be helpful,
because you want all the GPUs you're
scattering to do some local computation
on the different parts.
So the inverse of scatter is scatter.
So this should be very predictable.
The input is you have a bunch of pieces, each of which
reside on a particular rank.
And then when you do a gather, that's
with respect to a particular rank, rank 0,
it's going to just concatenate all the pieces together.
Again, gather isn't directly used,
but it's going to be a stepping stone to understand all gather.
So next is reduce.
So those of you who do functional programming are
probably familiar with what reduce is.
It's exactly the same.
The idea is that you start in the same starting point
as a gather.
And where the tensor is split up across multiple-- well,
you have some piece of data on each of the different ranks.
And then you're going to apply your reduction
operation to all of these and get that in, put that on rank 0.
So in this case, if you do a reduction with sum,
then you add these all up, you get six.
So you can think about gather as a reduction
where the operation is concatenation, if you will.
And of course, reduce is important to understanding
all reduce.
So let me pause there.
Those were just the warm ups. Just in case people
have any questions about what a collective operation is,
broadcast, scatter, gather, reduce.
[INAUDIBLE] NumPy, where is it?
Yeah?
So the question is, is this related
to broadcasting and NumPy?
I mean, I think it's conceptually the same idea,
where you have one thing that goes to many things.
Like in NumPy, if you have a scalar,
get broadcast to a tensor.
But the instantiation, this is for collective communication.
So it's a bit different.
So let's move on to something more interesting.
So all gather is what you do to-- basically,
you perform gather to all ranks, not just rank 0.
So remember what gather does.
It basically takes all the different pieces
and it just puts it on one rank, rank 0.
And now all gather just does it for every single rank.
That's what the all is for.
All means do it for all the output to all the ranks,
and gather is what you're doing to all the ranks.
So this is going to come up a bunch.
It's not important that you understand this statement
precisely, but later we'll see that each rank holds
part of the parameters.
And then what you need to do is all
gather the parameters to get the full parameters
for the full forward pass.
So in general, as we're doing training,
we're going to see a lot of this gather to do something
and then scatter and then gather and scatter again.
So reduce scatter is performing reduce on each dimension
and then scattering the results.
So let's say you have four devices and each of them
has some vector.
And so when we did a reduce before, we just had 0123,
and that got reduced to 6.
But now reduce scatter says that for each component
of this tensor, I'm going to do a reduction,
and then I'm going to put it on a different rank.
So the first dimension, I'm going to add these up, I get 6.
Now, for the second dimension, I'm going to add these up.
I get 10.
For third dimension, I'm going to process these.
For the fourth dimension, I'm going to process those.
So where this is going to show up, just to foreshadow things,
after the backward pass, when you sum what you're going to do
is each GPU will be dealing with different data.
And what you're doing is you need to sum all of the gradients
from the different shards.
And then you're going to redistribute this storage.
And then finally, all reduce.
If you understand all reduce gather and all gather,
it's basically you do one and then you do the other.
So what this does is reduce scatter, the same input as we
had before.
And remember, in reduce scatter, we
had 6, 10, 14, and 18 sit on different ranks.
And the all gather part of all reduce just
puts them all on the same--
everything on the same node.
So all reduce is in some sense the easiest to understand.
You have a bunch of tensors.
You reduce, in this case, some.
And then you replicate them on all the nodes.
So we're going to see this one actually first
when we do a data parallel where we sum the gradients
and then we replicate the full parameters.
So that's where we're actually going to start.
So maybe just focus your attention on all reduce.
Later, we're going to see how to get to fancier things like 0
or FSDP.
We need to break the all reduce into reduce scatter and all
gather, because then you can intervene
and you can manage things a bit more.
But for the basic version, all reduce is fine.
Finally, all to all.
This one is, in some ways, the most general.
You basically specify how each rank sends a particular message
to another rank.
And so here's a simple example where you
have the same input as before.
And what this is saying is that I
want to send 0 to this element to rank 0,
meaning keep it myself.
I'm going to send one to rank 1, two
to rank 2, and three to rank 3.
And then if I'm rank 1, I want to send four to rank 0, five
to rank 1, six to rank 2, and seven to rank 3.
So basically, the position here is
going to denote which rank is going
to be the ultimate destination.
And so if you look at the output, what happens
is that the first rank is going to receive everyone
who sent everything in column 0, because all these ranks are
sending these things to rank 0.
Similarly, for rank 1, all of the ranks
are sending this column to rank 1, and so on and so forth.
So this is going to be useful when for training MOEs.
And the intuition here is that each rank
has both a split of the data and also a subset of experts.
And basically, and the key idea of the MOE
is that it's dynamic routing.
You have to look at your data to figure out
which experts you need to route those activations to.
So it ends up being a all to all communication.
So if everything were balanced, meaning that every rank sent
the same number of bytes to every other rank,
then all to all, you can think about it
as essentially a transpose.
If you think about this as a matrix, all you're doing
is transposing that matrix.
But in general, all to all also handles unbalanced splits.
And I'm not showing this here, but you
can configure it to send any number of bytes
to any other rank.
But in general, you want the splits
to be as balanced as possible.
So remember [INAUDIBLE] MOE lecture
where we had load balancing to make sure that things were as
balanced as possible.
So morally, the ideal goal is to have all
to all look kind of like this.
So just to summarize, maybe a few helpful tips to remember
the terminology, because I just went through quite
a few different operations.
So reduce is, well, it's reduced.
It performs on some of associative commutative
operation.
Could be some, could be max, could be min.
Scatter is the inverse gather.
Scatter distributes, gather centralizes.
And all just means that the destination is all devices.
So that explains all reduce and all gather.
Let me pause there to take any questions
about collective communications.
Yeah?
For operations such as gathering where we basically [INAUDIBLE]
to rank 0, does that rank 0 [INAUDIBLE]?
Is it a particular GPU every time or can that rank 0 change?
Yeah.
So the question is when you do a gather or a reduce,
the target where you write the output, right now I said rank 0.
You'll see later in the code, you basically
specify the GPU ID or the rank and it goes there.
So it doesn't have to be determined way in advance,
but it has to be determined basically
when you execute the call.
Cool.
Anything else?
Yeah.
These are just conceptual building blocks, right?
They're not actually [INAUDIBLE].
Are these the actual [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, so the question is, are these just conceptual building
blocks or are they code?
So I'm showing these right now as just conceptual building
blocks, but we'll very quickly see how
these are implemented in code.
So before getting into the code, I
want to talk a bit about the hardware,
in particular how GPUs are connected,
because we already what's inside a GPU.
So let's talk about networking in general.
So this is a very classic picture.
You can tell from this very old looking image
that this is how computers, I mean, generally work.
So you have this server and then you have a bunch of CPUs.
There's a PCIe bus, which you connect things like your--
or used to connect things like your mouse and keyboard.
And then you have a bunch of GPUs sitting off of them
and you have some RAM.
And then this computer is connected
to ethernet to another computer, and so on and so forth.
So this is a particular setup.
It's a particular topology.
And GPUs on the same node, you use PCIe to communicate and GPUs
on different nodes, you have to go all the way through ethernet.
So this is like if you bought your gaming GPU
and you had hooked it up with your friend and was like,
I'm going to train some big model.
That's what you would have to do.
But if you're really serious about training,
then things look more like this.
This is the picture I showed in the very beginning
where you have the GPU and there's
something called NVLink and NVSwitch and InfiniBand.
So the typical setup is this.
And these numbers, eight is typical,
but this 256 is kind of made up.
So typically, you have eight GPUs per node.
And these are connected via NVIDIA's NVLink to a switch.
And just for calibration, if you use NVLink 5,
then you're getting 1.8 terabytes
per second of total bandwidth.
And remember, HBM for B200 was 8 terabytes per second.
So it's about 4x slower.
So I mean, this is still pretty fast
if you think about going between devices, but obviously,
not as fast as high bandwidth memory,
which is much slower than shared memory or L1 cache.
So basically, NVLink connects to the switch,
which means that from a programming perspective,
you can think about GPUs as connected to any other GPU.
You go GPU to any other GPU, and the hardware
takes care of transmitting that to the switch,
and the switch routes it.
So typically, what you will also have is that at some point,
you can't have NVSwitch and NVLink.
Because as your number of GPUs grows,
then you're going to have to put these nodes into pods, which
are connected by InfiniBand.
And the way InfiniBand works is that now there's
a bit more the-- so now the GPU doesn't connect directly
to another GPU.
It has to go through PCIe and goes through this kind
of special InfiniBand cable.
And you see that the speeds are much, much lower.
And then finally, if you run out of InfiniBand
and you have these huge pods, then
you need to connect them via ethernet.
And in ethernet, you have to go through PCIe
and that actually goes through the CPU, which as we'll see,
is even slower.
So it's kind of analogous to the kind of memory situation.
The more nodes you have, then the slower it's going to be.
You can't have an NVSwitch handling 100,000 GPUs.
So one note is that I alluded to this bypassing
the CPU, which is going to be an important thing from a hardware
perspective.
So if you have traditional ethernet, what happens
is that the GPU has to talk to the CPU to get its data copied.
So it basically has to copy the data to this.
The CPU has a kernel socket buffer.
Here kernel means not the GPU kernel,
but the CPU, traditional notion of a kernel.
And then it has to build some network packets,
copy to the network interface, and then ship it over.
So this generally introduces a lot of latency.
And so there's this technology called Remote Direct Memory
Access, RDMA, which allows a GPU to directly write or read
from another GPU's memory without using the CPU at all.
So obviously, if you're in NVLink land and NVSwitch land,
then you have RDMA.
InfiniBand also supports RDMA.
So if you're connected via InfiniBand,
then you can directly have GPUs connect to each other
without involving the CPU.
But standard ethernet does not.
There's two notable advancements I will mention.
So NVIDIA has been really pushing
the limits on what you can do with larger and larger pods.
So they have four of basically the B200's and the B300's.
They have something called NVL72,
which means that they have these trays of eight GPUs
but have nine of them.
And so basically, at the end of the day,
you have 72 GPUs that are all kind of NV switched
into one NVLink domain.
And if you remember, the NV link speeds are very fast.
So normally, if you're mortal, you
think, well OK, I have eight GPUs that
are interlinked really fast.
And then outside of that, then things get slowed down a lot.
But if you have a lot of money, you
can buy this really fancy hardware
and you can get really fast interconnects up to 72 GPUs.
And the other thing I'll mention is
that I said standard ethernet doesn't support RDMA,
but there has been progress on the ethernet front as well.
So there's something called RoCE, RDMA
over converged ethernet, where the ethernet actually
bypasses the CPU.
And this is sort of their answer to InfiniBand.
So InfiniBand generally is very expensive,
as is a lot of NVIDIA products.
But you can get pretty good performance
by using RDMA over converged ethernet.
And Meta had some paper showing that they were exploring this.
So [INAUDIBLE] may or may not have been trained
over converged ethernet.
So that's just a brief overview of what the hardware looks like.
You have GPUs.
They're connected via NVLink to NVSwitch over some domain,
maybe 8, maybe 72.
And then it's InfiniBand from there.
And now let's talk about how do you program this.
So at the very lowest level, there's something called
the NVIDIA Collective Communications Library,
NCCL or "nickel," which translates the collective
operations, the all reduce, reduce broadcasts,
into the actual low level packets that are sent between
GPUs.
So what a NCCL does is when you use NCCL,
it's basically like saying, I want to all reduce.
And then NCCL goes and figures out what
is the topology of the hardware, figures out
the path between different GPUs, and then
it actually launches the GPU kernels to send and receive
data.
Because at the end of the day, remember,
everything that runs on a GPU is a kernel.
So there are communication kernels as well
that actually do communication with other GPUs.
So we're not going to look too much more into NCCL,
but just know that it exists.
And then we're going to actually go to PyTorch.
So maybe before that, any questions about hardware?
Yeah.
Can you describe-- there's a rack and a tray.
Can I describe physically a rack and a tray, like what a rack is
and what a tray is?
So for the NV72, so I'm not a hardware expert,
but a rack, I mean, is literally, I mean,
you've seen data centers, literally a rack.
And each tray is something that has--
so the G stands for a [? great. ?]
So there's two CPUs.
And each CPU is connected to four GPUs.
So each tray has eight GPUs on it.
And they're stacked and everything
is connected to this NVSwitch.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE].
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so the question is, what is the difference between
Yeah.
So RDMA, you can think about it as more of a desiderata.
RDMA means that one GPU can read and write
from another GPU's memory.
And there's multiple ways to do RDMA.
One is to use NVLink and NVSwitch
and another way is to use InfiniBand.
So InfiniBand and NVSwitch and NVLink
are more the hardware, what pieces, what cables and switches
are there.
And RDMA is more operation, what happens
[INAUDIBLE]
when you're communicating.
Yeah.
For example, this [? advancement ?] RDMA
[INAUDIBLE]
over converged ethernet is another way to do RDMA.
Yeah?
Is NCCL optimized for multi-node clusters?
Because obviously, it seems intuitive [INAUDIBLE].
But for RDMA based processes, would NCCL be optimal for that?
So the question is, is NCCL optimized
for multi-node clusters?
So I don't know the details of how they have or have not
optimized it.
All I can say is that NVIDIA has been basically optimizing
their entire stack for inference and training
of these large models, because their main customers are
the major providers of language models.
So I would be surprised if they haven't thought of optimizing
for those type of workloads.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah?
So the question is, what happens if you have nine GPUs?
How do you distribute the workload across those?
I guess it kind of depends on how
the nine lands in your setup.
For example, a lot of times you'll have--
let's say you have eight GPUs per node.
So then the ninth one would be on a different node.
And if you don't have NVLink connecting them,
then that's going to be really bad, because that's
going to be one node which is not providing
that much compute and also very expensive to communicate with.
But if you, let's say, had everything
were connected by NVSwitch, then it
would be much more reasonable.
One more question and I'm going to move on.
So how is this different from TPUs?
So [INAUDIBLE] described TPUs a bit more.
So I mean, let's see.
What can I say quickly about this?
So TPUs are generally much simpler objects.
I'm not too familiar with the details of what
each of these components corresponds to,
but maybe we can talk about it offline.
So let's actually get down to some code
to take advantage of this hardware.
So PyTorch conveniently has a torch
distributed library that provides
a clean interface into these collective operations.
So you don't have to explicitly think about NCCL.
And in fact, this library also supports different backends
for different hardware.
So if you are on GPUs, then you would use the NCCL backend.
And if you were on CPUs, then there's
something called gloo which still allows you to--
like I said, parallel processing has been around
for a long time before GPUs.
And you can do these collect operations on CPUs as well.
This library also supports higher level models
and algorithms such as SFTP, but we're not
going to use those in the course because we're building things
from scratch.
All right.
So let's walk through some basic examples
of collective operations.
So there's this function called spawn,
which takes another function I'm going to call,
and it says I'm going to run this replicated four times where
four is the world size.
So let's see what this does.
This is actually a wrapper I wrote just
to hack around the fact that I can't do multiprocessing
in this lecture.
So normally what you would do is you
call Torch's multiprocessing.spawn
and you call the function.
But I'm going to do this branch which disables distributed.
So let's just go through that.
So now I'm in this function that it's
supposed to be running asynchronously for each process.
So remember, world size is the number of processes
and the rank is either 0 or 1 or 2 all the way up to world
size minus 1.
And so there are world size number
of these functions that are each running
on a process at the same time.
So I'm on rank 0 right now.
So what do I do?
There's a setup.
You basically configure the master address and port.
Notice that this is not actually how the GPUs are
going to communicate.
This is more for general metadata and coordination.
The actual data goes through NCCL.
Otherwise, it would be very, very slow.
And if you have Cuda available, then you
can use the NCCL backend.
I'm on my laptop, so I'm going to use the gloo backend.
OK, so now I'm here.
Pretend I have four of these processes running.
So there's this barrier function, which is useful as--
it's a synchronization barrier.
So basically, if I see this, then it
waits for all the processes to get to this point.
So basically, you can think about all the processes
are running asynchronously.
So I don't really control.
One could completely finish before the other.
They might finish interleaved in any way.
So if I want to make sure that there's
some code that is executed before other code,
I put these synchronization barriers in.
So now the downside of putting more barriers in
is that, well, you end up kind of waiting potentially
unnecessarily.
So let's try an all reduce.
So I'm going to create this tensor, 0, 1, 2, 3.
And I have my rank.
Just to make it more interesting,
each rank is going to have a different tensor.
I'm going to print out what I have before the all reduce.
So now I'm going to skip over here and see
what gets printed out.
So rank 0 before all reduce has 0, 1, 2, 3.
Rank 1 has 1, 2, 3, 4, and so on.
It's the same example as I showed before.
Notice that the print statements are coming in whatever order
the hardware feels like it, because it's running async.
But all the data is there.
So now if I do all reduce, and this you pass in--
this is a PyTorch function.
It passes in this tensor.
You pass in the reduction operation, which is a sum.
And I'm going to say don't do async.
And what this does is it calls, in this case, it would be gloo,
but it could be NCCL, in which case, it
would spin up the Cuda kernels.
It would do the communication.
It takes care of everything for you.
And then it basically writes in place to the data.
So after the all reduce, I have the all reduce operation,
remember, which is the sum of each of these columns
but replicated across all the ranks.
So that's all reduce.
And if you wanted to be fancier and do async,
then you could say async equals true.
But then it would screw up all these print statements.
So I'm trying to put more barriers than I would normally
would.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, question?
So the question is the rank the GPU.
For this class, the rank is the GPU.
So let's try another example here.
So I'm going to do a reduce scatter.
So here, I'm going to create an input, which
is 0 through the world size.
And I'm going to have the output.
I'm going to allocate the output.
And so what does this look like before I do the reduce scatter?
It looks like, let's see, this, where it's the same input
and the output happens to be zeros,
but it could be just anything.
And then I do the reduce scatter tensor.
Here instead of writing in place,
I have an output tensor and an input tensor.
I say I want to do the sum and then
afterwards, I get basically the input is not touched,
but the output I get the reduction
of each component written into the respective ranks.
[INAUDIBLE]
So yeah, question?
So the question is, how does it work
to do the all reduces asynchronous?
So what this means is that this is like a monolithic operation.
You say go do the all reduce.
And it's spinning up Cuda kernels.
It's going to do the communication.
And remember, Cuda is already kind of async with respect
to the processes, and now we have
all the processes being async.
And the point is that this code just would return.
And then you could do other things.
So a typical thing, which I'm not
going to talk about this class, is overlapping computation
and communication.
So for example, you can do this operation,
and then you can go ahead and load some other data
for the next step, which is independent of this operation.
And then when you want to make sure that you actually are done,
then you can call a weight or a barrier.
So let's do the final one, which is all gather.
So by now, I think you get the idea.
Here I'm going to set as the input
the output of the reduce scatter.
I'm going to allocate an output.
So before the all gather, it looks like this.
I have my results from the reduce scatter here.
The output is just allocated.
It happens to have some values in it, but don't worry about it.
And then after I do the all gather into tensor,
and then I will have all the different inputs gathered
onto all the different ranks.
And you can see here that, indeed,
proof via example that all reduce
is equal to reduce scatter plus all gather.
And then just to wrap things up, just as I started by setup, then
I clean up, which it's good practice to clean up.
So that was your first example of a Torch distributed program.
So let's do some benchmarking.
This will be quick, since I want to actually move on to part two.
So how fast does communication happen?
So let's do an all reduce.
So here, I'm going to all reduce with 100 million elements.
Oops.
Sorry, I messed this up.
So all reduce.
So I'm going to create this tensor
with this number of elements.
And remember, just like before when we do benchmarking,
we warm up first.
And here, I'm going to call the Cuda synchronize and also
the barrier, just to make sure that because there's
two forms of asynchrony here, the Cuda kernels
and the different processes.
And just want to make sure everything
is kind of not running and is done before I start the time.
And I'm going to do the all reduce.
And then wait again with the synchronize in the barrier
and stop the time.
So remember, this is running for every single rank.
So if I look at the output, here for rank 0, 2, 1, 3,
I have a different time potentially,
because they're all different processes.
Each of them is going to report a certain measurement.
And if you want to report one number,
you can take the average, for example.
So now one thing that is useful to do,
which is analogous to when we were computing MFU,
is to measure the effective bandwidth.
And the idea here is that, well, this took 1.6 milliseconds.
How much-- is that good or bad?
So to compute the effective bandwidth, what
we're going to do is to compute essentially
how many bytes were sent and should be
sent during this computation.
And then if you divide by the total time,
then you get the effective bandwidth.
So the size of what I'm sending around
is the size of each element times the number of elements.
So that's basically the number of bytes of this data tensor.
How many bytes get actually sent?
So this needs some unpacking.
So for all reduce, if you think about,
let's just say for simplicity, you do a rank 0 plus rank 1
plus rank 2 plus rank 3.
You need to iterate this world size minus 1 steps,
because there's a world size minus 1 addition operations.
So that's this factor.
There's a 2, because you need to both send and reduce.
And then you multiply by the size of the payload.
So that's the total number of sent bytes.
And the total duration is the wall clock time that it took.
And then you multiply by the world size,
because it's the total amount that all the ranks have waited.
And the bandwidth is the bytes sent
divided by the total duration.
So in this case, you get something
like about 400 gigabytes per second.
So a few notes here.
One is that the effective bandwidth,
if you look at this expression, size times 2 times
world size minus 1 divided by world size times duration.
So as world size increases, this world size
minus 1 divided by world size essentially converges to 1.
So you're effectively left with 2 times the size
bytes over the duration.
So this is essentially the bandwidth.
Notice that this is independent of the world size,
which is good.
So if you grow the number of GPUs you have,
the bandwidth doesn't change.
It is also independent of the topology, which
is something that kind of NCCL figures out whether you're
going to pass the messages in a kind of a ring or a tree
topology.
So yeah.
So that is all reduce.
And for reduce scatter, this is very similar.
So I'm going to create the inputs and the outputs,
warm up, perform the operation, and time it.
So notice that the reduce scatter has these timings.
And you can also measure the effective bandwidth here,
the number of bytes that were in the input.
You have the number of bytes that were sent.
Here there is no 2x here.
And then the total duration, you divide by that,
you get the bandwidth.
So here, the bandwidth is--
it should be very similar.
I guess sometimes there's some stochasticity,
but it's in the kind of 400s.
So a few notes here.
All reduce is, remember, as we stated, reduce
scatter plus an all gather.
And so all reduce, naturally, is moving twice the amount of data,
because reduce scatter has some cost, all gather has some cost,
and all reduce is doing twice as much work.
And it takes twice the amount of time.
But the two cancel out, so you get the same kind of bandwidth.
So that is the end of part one.
Maybe any questions before I move to part two?
Yeah.
Why did you do that synchronized for [INAUDIBLE]?
So why do we have to do the synchronized for the Cuda
kernel?
So at the end of the day, we are still doing Cuda operations.
We have just multiple processes, each with a GPU,
doing some Cuda operations.
So if you're doing a Cuda operation, remember, by default,
it's async.
So when you reach the next line in Python,
that Cuda operation might not be done.
So we need to wait always to make sure it's
[INAUDIBLE]
done by synchronizing.
So do you have to do barrier first and then synchronize?
I'm not sure.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
I think one problem is if you barrier first
and then the Cuda might not be done running,
and you just immediately go to the barrier.
And then you are still each independently synchronizing
the different Cuda kernels, which means that you're not
really synchronized.
If all those operations just return,
the barrier doesn't really do anything.
OK, let me move on.
So now let's actually start thinking
about how you train models.
So we're just going to walk through a very bare bones
implementation of training MLPs, multilayer MLPs.
I guess that's redundant.
It's multilayer perceptrons already.
And remember that MLPs are the ones that
are the actual compute bottleneck in the transformer.
So this is actually pretty representative of what
you'll see.
So data parallelism, tensor parallelism,
and pipeline parallelism.
And the picture I want you to have in your head
is this picture.
So this is a little bit of a schematic,
so don't think too deeply about this,
but it's more of a way to conceptualize how you're cutting
your data and parameters.
So data parallelism says, I'm going
to split the data into pieces.
And then each of the GPUs is going
to be responsible for part of the data,
and I'm going to just do normal--
I'm going to keep track of all the parameters
and do normal model training.
And then I need to synchronize.
So let me explain how this works.
So I'm going to generate some sample data.
So there's a batch size of 128.
Number of dimensions, 1,024.
So this is a batch size by num dim matrix, data matrix.
And let's jump into this data parallelism.
So the way that it's going to work
is that you have this data matrix.
And I'm going to break up the rows into world size pieces.
And in this case, four.
And each rank is going to get a piece.
So the number of dimensions, the batch size.
So I'm going to call the local batch size, basically the batch
size divided by the world size, which
is every row that GPU sees, it's going to have 32 data points.
And this is just indexing.
Start index data start to end gets you the slice of that data.
And I'm going to just put it on that rank.
So at this point, each GPU has now
a distinct data tensor, which is the part
that they're responsible for.
Now, in practice, each rank should probably
load its own data rather than have this bottleneck,
but this is just for illustrative purposes.
So let's instantiate the MLP.
So here, I assume we have layers.
And num layers.
And for each of the layers, I'm going to have just a num
dim by num dim matrix.
So I'm just going to initialize a random set of parameters.
And then I'm going to feed that into optimizer.
So here's the training loop.
So in the forward pass, I take the data.
So remember, data is not all the data.
It's just if I'm rank 2, then I only get B2 part of the data.
I'm going to just go through the number of layers
and do a forward pass.
And then I'm going to do a backward pass.
And then normally, this would be it.
But now, remember, every rank has different data.
Therefore, the gradients are going to be different as well.
So this is the key step that makes data parallelism work.
We're going to synchronize the gradients
across all the workers.
This is the only difference between standard training
and DDP.
It's actually pretty nice and elegant.
So basically, for all the parameters,
I'm going to do an all reduce of parem.grad.
And I'm going to average.
And then after this all reduce is done, then now at this point,
each of the ranks has the exact same gradients.
And then I'm just going to update the parameters.
So it's kind of really elegant, I find,
because it's basically standard training where you apply it
to your local batch, but you just insert this
after the backward pass.
Let's just average all the gradients via this all reduce.
It's a one line code change, and then the parameters get updated.
So as you're training, each rank is basically
performing parameter updates as if it had all the data on it,
but it's only actually processing a part of the data.
So that's basically DDP or the first type of data parallel.
Any questions about this?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So the question is, can you only do this
with batch size greater than 1?
Yes.
So your batch size has to be at least world size for this
to really make sense.
And usually, it should probably be quite a bit larger.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah?
Yeah.
So the question is, should the batch size
be a multiple of world size?
And that also would be nice.
Yes.
I mean, if it's not, then you can pad it
with zeros or something.
[INAUDIBLE]?
So there's ways, but it's just easier for everyone if it is.
What would it look like for a transform-based [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, so the question is, what would this look
like for a transformer?
It would actually be basically the same.
The DDP has the nice thing that is very modular.
You do the forward pass.
I mean, DDP just averages the parameters here.
It doesn't care what your forward pass looks like.
OK, let me move on.
So that's DDP.
So just to summarize, the losses are different across the ranks.
The gradients are also initially different.
But they are all reduced to be the same across the ranks.
And therefore, the parameters all
remain the same across ranks.
So next lecture, [? Tatsu ?] is going
to talk about fancier data parallelism, FSDP and 0.
And the idea there is, as I've alluded to,
here we use all reduce.
It's a very simple monolithic operation,
but it does require holding all the models, parameters
in memory.
But what if the model parameters don't fit in memory?
Then you're going to have to be more clever,
and that's the topic for the next class.
So let me talk about tensor parallelism.
So here, the idea is we're going to cut this way
and we're not going to cut the data.
We're going to cut essentially each layer.
And so each rank is going to get part of each layer.
And generally, this means that we're
going to have to transfer a lot more data.
We'll discuss this a bit later.
So what does tensor parallel look like?
So we're just going to assume we have this data.
Every rank has all the data just for simplicity.
And here, remember, the data is batch size times num dim.
And I'm going to define a local num dim
dim to be-- for this rank, I only
am responsible for a subset of the dimensions.
So the picture here is that each model still has all the layers
here for all the layers, but the parameters now
are num dim times local num dim.
So if this were one of the parameter
matrices for one layer, I would be splitting down the columns.
So this is also known as column tensor parallel.
You can also do it by rows, but we're not going
to talk about that right now.
So now what does the forward pass look like?
So I'll go through all the layers
and I'm going to compute activations.
So I start with x the data.
And I'm going to access the parameters at layer.
And notice that this is only a slice of the parameters.
So if I'm on rank 1, I only get this part of the matrix.
But I can still proceed.
I can apply this non-linearity, because this
is element wise anyway.
But now what I'm going to do is I'm going
to communicate activations.
So if I have a data matrix, rank 1
has activations for part of the activations
for this part of the matrix.
Rank 1 has part of the activations for this matrix
and so on and so forth.
And I need to basically put all the activations
on all the ranks.
But we know how to do that.
We introduced all gather as a collective primitive.
So this is all the activations.
So this is the batch size times local num dim, which is
the shape of the activations.
And then I'm doing an all gather.
Sorry, so this is the allocating memory for the activations.
So x is the actual part of the activation.
So this is batch size times local num dim.
And all gather says each rank has x and each rank
is going to allocate activations,
which is a list, one for each world size.
And then after the all gather, x is
going to be copied into each of the respective location
activations.
So then once I gather all the activations,
I concatenate them to form the full dimensional x, which
is batch size times num dim.
Any questions about column tensor parallel?
So this is done for every layer.
We now notice one difference between data parallel
is now we have to muck around with the model.
Data parallel is very elegant, because it's splitting by data.
The model is treated as a module.
But now we have to muck around with the model.
And this is strongly leveraging the fact
that if you want to do a matrix multiplication,
you can split it up into a set of smaller matrix
multiplications.
We can do those on different ranks,
and then we can gather the results.
[INAUDIBLE] gradients are still [INAUDIBLE].
When it comes to the back propagation,
Yeah.
So now the question is, what happens in backprop?
Now, in the backprop, you have your activations
and you have to reduce scatter to all the different gradients.
So in some ways, all gather and reduce scatter
have this kind of duality, where in forward, you're
all gathering, in the backward, you're reduce scattering.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah?
So the question is, is that done automatically by autograd?
So none of this--
well, OK.
So if you just call .backward, it's not going to do it,
because there's no parallelism in that.
But PyTorch has all these things that
[INAUDIBLE] To what extent do I need to change
are done automatically for you.
my code and [INAUDIBLE]?
So what is done for you and versus automatically?
Here we're managing things fairly explicitly,
which means I'm not doing the backward pass,
but you would have to manage and call the reduce scatter
yourself.
And that's by design, because this is 336,
building language models from scratch.
In practice, you probably wouldn't have to do that.
OK, so let's do pipeline parallelism quickly.
So the idea behind pipeline parallelism
is we're going to split the network this way.
So each rank is going to get a subset of the layers now.
Within each layer, it's going to get all the dimensions,
and it's also going to get all the--
well, one of the ranks is going to get all the data.
Every rank is going to see all the data in some form.
So this is the way it's going to work.
So we have all the data, which is, again,
the batch size times num dim.
And I'm going to split up the layers.
So local num layers is going to be the number of layers
that a particular rank is going to handle.
And so now I'm going to have local params, which
is basically only-- there's local number of layers
number of them.
But within each layer, I'm going to do the num dim by num dim.
So one thing, maybe [INAUDIBLE] will talk more
about this on Wednesday, is this idea of micro-batches.
So maybe I'll just present this and explain
why I'm doing things this way.
So in addition to splitting up the layers,
I'm also going to split up the batch
into a bunch of micro-batches.
So if I'm rank 0, then I get the data,
and I'm going to chunk it up into a number of micro-batches.
And for each micro-batch, what I'm going to do
is receive it from the previous rank,
and then do the feed forward pass only on the layers that
are assigned to this rank.
And then I'm going to send to the next rank.
So here I'm actually using these receive and send,
which are pointwise operations.
So I didn't cover those before, but they're fairly explanatory.
This basically says I'm rank and I'm going
to send this tensor over to--
sorry, I'm going to receive this tensor from rank minus 1.
And this says I'm going to send tensor x to rank plus 1.
So basically, the reason why I'm talking about micro-batches is--
and [? Tatsu ?] will talk more about this on Wednesday--
is that in pipeline parallelism, so you have
one rank that gets the data.
It processes some of the layers, and then
it sends it to the next GPU, and it process some of the layers.
And it then sends it to the next GPU.
So this is a very natural way of dividing a deep network.
But the problem is that you get these
what are called pipeline bubbles, where while you're not
processing, you're kind of waiting around for other tensors
to process.
And this ends up being quite inefficient.
So the idea behind micro-batches is that you break it up
into smaller batches, so you can process it quickly,
send it on to the next one.
So this can reduce the number of pipeline bubbles.
So the other thing I will mention
that is not handled in this very kind of naive version
is the idea of overlapping communication and computation,
which is actually very important to pipeline parallelism.
This basically gives you the right structure.
If you put an I before these, then it becomes kind of async.
You have to add more things to manage the code.
And the idea here is that you want to be--
while you're computing here, you can be
receiving data or sending data.
So computation and communication should overlap.
So that reduces the amount of time you actually spend waiting.
So a few things that are kind of missing here, which we'll
hopefully fill in next time.
So the communication versus computation overlap,
which is especially crucial in pipeline parallelism.
I didn't mention in data parallelism,
this also happens, because I just did a forward pass
and then at the end, I'm just doing all these all reduces.
But if you're clever, then on the backward pass,
as soon as the gradients are done,
you can start sending that.
And that's something that will be
explored in the assignment two.
And this, again, allows you to just overlap communication
and computation more.
We had some questions about what about general models.
Again, I think this MLP gives you
essentially most of what you need
for understanding the basics.
Some of the larger models just require a lot more bookkeeping,
so it's harder to see the core algorithms.
There are other types of parallelism
that we haven't covered.
So sequence parallelism takes a whole sequence
and chops it up into pieces.
And that allows you to parallelize the attention
computation, expert parallelism, which allows you to parallelize
the experts for MOEs.
And this is where the all to all that I mentioned comes in.
And then also different combinations
of different parallelization techniques, which also
will show up in the assignment.
So one thing to note is that which
parallelism technique you choose is
going to be strongly dependent on the hardware.
For example, tensor parallelism.
There's a lot of communication, because for every layer,
you need to send all these activations, which
are fairly big.
So generally, tensor parallelism happens within a node on NVLink
or where you have high bandwidth.
Whereas you wouldn't do tensor parallelism
past an NVLink domain.
Whereas a pipeline parallelism, you'll see people using it.
And generally, this can tolerate much slower interconnects.
So some of the decentralized training work
uses pipeline parallel, because your nodes are--
GPUs are halfway across the world.
But you wouldn't want to do tensor parallel in that setting.
So sometimes when you look at these combinations,
it will be tensor parallel within a node
and then pipe data parallel or FSDP
and then pipeline parallelism if you need it.
There's other effects, such as if you do data parallel,
you might be able to do data parallel quite a bit.
But then you start hitting to something
called the critical batch size, where
if you start increasing the batch size too much,
it doesn't actually help you, in which case
you're kind of wasting your compute
and then you're better off using tensor parallel.
So there's a bunch of these considerations,
which we'll talk more about as we go through the class.
So final note.
So TPUs came up a little bit.
One thing to note is that on purpose, we are using PyTorch
and not just using PyTorch, but really using
the collective operations in a very primitive way,
so you can see mechanically what's happening.
Another approach, especially if you're in [INAUDIBLE] TPU land,
is that you can simply define the model and the starting
strategy.
And the compiler actually handles a lot
of the decision of how to--
basically, what kind of communication operations
you need.
You basically say, well, this piece of data
needs to be here and here and here.
And then the compiler does some magic to figure out what.
So that's appealing.
But obviously, it would take a lot of the joy
out of actually building things from scratch.
Just to summarize, so there's many ways to parallelize.
You can cut by data, cut by tensor or expert,
cut by pipeline or sequence.
We looked at data parallelism.
We only did DDP.
Next time we'll do FSDP and 0.
Tensor parallelism, as I mentioned,
requires very fast interconnects.
Pipeline less so.
But you need to really work hard to reduce these pipeline
bubbles.
And then maybe at a high level, we
see this pattern come up a lot.
So you can either recompute or store in memory
when we were talking about things
like activation checkpointing or when we're working with GPUs.
Or in this case, you can think about an extension of this
as that you can store on a different GPU.
From that perspective, you look at the data parallel.
You're doing redundant work in some sense,
because every rank is actually updating its parameters
and keeping track of all the parameters.
But the reason you're doing that is
that you don't have to move the optimizer state across.
So one thing is that hardware is getting faster.
But in some sense, we'll always want bigger models.
So this idea of having a hierarchical structure
will always be there.
So that's it for today.
So next Wednesday, [? Tatsu ?] will do more of a deep dive
on more parallelism techniques.