So today we're going to talk about data.
And where we are is that you know how
to train a model, given data.
Last time we saw evaluations, so we know what a good model is.
And for the next two lectures, this week
we're going to focus on what data should we train on.
And I want to argue that data is the most important thing
to get right in language models.
And one justification for this is
if you look at what companies actually disclose--
so here is the Llama 3 paper.
They have full transparency into the architecture--
well of course, because it's open-weight model--
they even tell you about their training procedures,
but they don't say anything about their data.
So they just say, we train for a variety of data sources
and do some stuff.
And there's good reasons for this secrecy.
One is that data is your competitive secret sauce.
Competitive dynamics.
You don't want your competitors to know what you're doing.
And the second thing, which we'll
talk a little bit more about, is copyright liability.
You don't want to get sued if you tell people you're training
on certain types of data.
So data is a long topic in machine learning.
And before foundation models, data work
meant you annotate-- label data for supervised learning.
Nowadays there's less manual annotation--
at least in pre-training-- but there's still
a lot of curation and cleaning work that needs to be done.
And so fundamentally, this hasn't really changed.
Data has always been a bottleneck,
and always will be a bottleneck because it's
in some sense a long-tail problem,
and that scales with human effort.
So if you have a lot of people trying to work on the problem,
well, there's only so many people
that can work on architectures and systems.
But data, well, that's-- especially if you're training
a foundation model that's trying to do all these things,
you can [? paralyze ?] that effort easily.
So that's why these data teams and these model developers
are actually quite big.
So data comes in at different stages of the pipeline.
Today we're focusing mostly on pre-training.
So pre-training, you take raw data--
these are documents from the web.
Then you move into mid-training where
you train on more high quality data
to enhance certain capabilities, and give long context, things
like that.
And then finally post training, where
you're training on things like chat transcripts,
or if you're doing reinforcement learning,
you get some environments that you're training on.
This becomes more task specific.
In practice the lines are a bit blurry,
and there could be more than three stages.
But this is a basic template.
The trend is that we go from training
on large amounts of low quality data
to smaller amounts of high quality data.
So as a result of this process--
you'll see in the literature when we talk about the base
model, This usually means after pre-training and mid training,
instruct models or chat models, or post-training.
But of course, the lines are becoming
blurry enough that what is the base model anymore
is really unclear.
And more recently, the largest models, there's no base model.
There's just Qwen3.5-397B-A17B, and that's it.
You don't see the intermediate checkpoints.
So for models that are open source like OLMo from AI2,
you can see everything that's happening.
And so, we'll study some of these models.
So for example, in pre-training, there's a bunch of sources which
we'll talk about what these mean, but--
web pages, academic papers, math pages, proofs, and so on.
There's mid-training-- higher quality web data,
instruction data, bunch of synthetic data often goes here.
And then finally post-training, there is a bunch of chat logs.
There are more math and reasoning,
and coding, you do safety at this point as well.
So what are all these datasets?
How do you choose them, and how do you process them?
So that's the main question.
So in the spirit of the class, we're going to talk about data.
I'm going to go start from scratch.
So where does data come from?
So one might hear in the hallway,
oh, language models are trained on the entire internet.
So first of all, this doesn't really quite type-check.
Because for that to be true, it would
have to be an agent that-- like an RL agent that goes
on the internet and does stuff.
But that's not actually how pre-training works.
Slightly more accurately, it's trained on the public world
wide web, but this is not quite accurate for reasons
I'll explain.
OK, so first of all, the web is actually a bunch of live servers
that just exist in the world, and you can connect to.
So take any website-- you can go and download the page.
Or, you can basically send a request and get back a response.
So you can't actually train on these live servers
unless you're training an RL agent.
So typically what you do is you have a crawler,
or someone builds a crawler, not necessarily you.
The crawler needs to discover what web pages are out there,
starting with the seed set, and it downloads the discovered web
pages as it is crawling.
But still, can't just run a crawl
and download all the web pages on the internet,
and there's a few reasons for this.
One is that a lot of the web content is actually dynamic.
So especially these days, a lot of sites are apps.
The URL isn't even as full [? of ?] specification
of the content, it's just an app that you interact with,
and you need to often click buttons or submit forms
to access content.
For example, if you're on Discord or something,
it's not like you can just crawl Discord and get all the content
on Discord.
So that's one kind of thing, and a lot of content
is actually known as in the deep web, which is not just
doing web page crawling and following
hyperlinks, which is a very of traditional model of web
crawling.
The second thing is that authentication.
So some pages need a login, an account, and generally
you have to pay.
For example, there's Facebook, X, LinkedIn, New York Times.
There's actually huge amounts of content
that are actually locked up behind these walled gardens.
So these are technically on the internet or on the web,
but you can't just build a crawler and go crawl Facebook.
I guess if you're Facebook, you can crawl--
you don't need to crawl Facebook, you have the data,
and you can train a model.
Or if you're X AI, you can train on X. But if you're anyone else,
you can't actually access this content.
OK, suppose you don't have the authentication issue.
There's still potential restrictions here.
So there's something called robots.txt,
and this is a file that is usually
placed at the root level of a directory, such as nytimes.com,
and it basically tells you what you're
allowed to crawl and whatnot.
So these things are-- a lot of things are disallowed,
such as OAI-SearchBot, or PerplexityBot, QuoraBot.
I think basically, ChatGPT-User, ClaudeBot, and all these things.
OK, so this is not a tech--
this is not a legal restriction, this
is just like, you're supposed to be a good citizen
and look at robots.txt.
And if your name is on that list,
then you should not crawl it.
That's basically the-- not even a contract,
that is the thing you're supposed to do.
A lot of websites now use something like Cloudflare
to detect and block bot activity.
So sometimes you've gone to a website,
and it gives you a CAPTCHA.
That's because somehow, some algorithm
has detected that you might be a bot,
and then it's making sure you're human.
And if you're actually a bot, then, well, you can't--
I mean, you could try to get around this,
but generally this is an obstacle in your way.
A website might block certain IP addresses or countries,
and they might have rate limits.
So there's technical restrictions
on what you can actually crawl, and then there's
also legal restrictions.
So websites have terms of service
that say, if you go to a website,
you have to obey this contract to use the website.
And the terms of service often will say, if you're a bot,
go away.
You cannot use this, the content of the site for AI training,
or whatever it might be.
And also, even if terms of service don't say anything,
the content of the website might have a license,
or you might not have a license to train.
And we'll talk more about this in a bit.
So there's legal restrictions on what
you are allowed to train on.
These things are also evolving over time.
So there's a nice paper by Shane Longpre
called Consent in Crisis, and what
they did is they examined the restrictions--
both the technical restrictions, robots.txt,
and the legal restrictions, the term of service,
for various URLs in common datasets,
which we'll talk about later.
And the conclusion was that the restrictions
have increased over time.
So here's a graphic that shows-- the top one shows robots.txt.
And if you just look at this red,
that's the full restrictions.
And up until 2023, everything was fairly constant.
And then up until mid 2023, all of a sudden
you see the amount of the fraction of websites
that have full restrictions on it has grown to almost 50% here.
And for terms, there's a similar trend where I guess in 2016,
no one really put any terms on their pages.
And now most pages put some terms, and most of the terms
say you can't use this for AI.
So even though it was possible to crawl the internet back in,
let's say 2020, the internet actually,
at least what you can legally crawl, is actually much smaller.
So of course, these are guidelines.
And sometimes, either intentionally
or not intentionally, you could violate these things.
So this is-- sometimes you get into these situations where
there's this guy who--
what was this?
I forget the name of this site--
was complaining about Anthropic crawling them,
hitting their servers a million times
in 24 hours, which was not good.
And then Read the Docs was also getting hammered.
So there was a period where, which I think probably
has hopefully been corrected by now, that crawlers
were hammering websites.
And there the-- here, this is interesting,
is like even before talking about copyright issues,
there's, I think, problems with crawling either violating
terms of service, or robots.txt, or just low up-down,
generating a lot of server load, which this costs money
for the person hosting it and also degrades service
for everyone else trying to use it.
So there are issues with crawling.
And then, of course, there's copyright,
which we'll talk about soon.
That's a whole other complex can of worms.
And then finally, there's these things called shadow libraries,
which are also part of the web.
So examples are LibGen, or Anna's Archive.
And these completely disregard copyright and bypass paywalls.
So someone has collected a ton of data-- usually
books and articles that are all copyrighted,
and people have to pay for these--
and have made them available for free.
And there have been a lot of takedown orders, lawsuits,
and these are blocked, but usually these
are circumvented because they just make
servers in other countries.
And the people doing this argue that this is making free
what's freely available, what should have been freed,
but generally from a legal perspective,
this is piracy and copyright infringement.
And we'll come back to this point later.
So there are a lot of books and papers on these shadow
libraries.
So the summary so far, the internet
is a huge and messy and scary place,
and you can't actually get all of it.
There are technical restrictions,
there's legal restrictions on what data one can access.
So now next time someone says, I trained on the internet,
you can tell them all these things you learned.
So now let's go to the second part of what data can we use,
and this has to do with copyright.
So suppose you were able to obey the terms of service,
and you are really a good citizen,
and you obey the rate limits.
Now, there's still a question of are you
allowed to train on this data?
And this is a ongoing question that
has not been fully resolved, but there
has been a bunch of developments in the last year.
So the legal context for thinking about this question
falls into intellectual property law,
and this is a system that is trying
to incentivize the creation of intellectual goods.
So I think it's--
remember, the spirit of the law is
to not just technically say no to everything,
but to incentivize the creation of intellectual goods.
And there's many forms of intellectual property
that are covered.
There's copyrights, patents, trademarks and secrets-- sorry,
trademarks, and trade secrets.
The thing that is most relevant for language model data
is copyright law.
So copyright law has a fairly long history going back
to the 1700s in England.
And so 1709 was the first time that governments and courts
started actually regulating copyright
for this goal of incentivizing innovation and creation.
And in the US, more recently, the Copyright Act of 1976
is what I think defines a lot of modern copyright.
So copyright protection applies to original works
of authorship fixed in any tangible medium of expression,
yada, yada, yada.
So a few notes.
So not everything is copyrightable.
In particular, collections are not copyrightable.
So for example, if you have a telephone directory,
unless there is some creativity in how you arrange things,
this is not really copyrightable.
And furthermore, copyright applies to the expression, not
the idea.
So you can't copyright an idea, like you can't copyright
the quick-sort algorithm.
You can copyright the implementation
of a quick-sort algorithm, but not the quicksort algorithm.
So one thing that happened in 1976
is that the barrier to getting a copyright was relaxed a lot.
So more things are copyright.
So it used to be that you had to publish something
to have something copyright.
Now things just have to be fixed.
And what that means is that registration of any sort
is not required for copyright protection.
This is in contrast to patents.
Patents you have to go pay a lot of money to get a patent,
and you have to file a patent.
But the threshold for copyright is very low.
For example, you put something on your website,
it's copyrighted.
That's it.
Now if you want to sue someone, you
have to go get it registered, but it only costs $65.
Which is much smaller than the lawyer fees
that you'll probably pay, so it's really
still a very low bar.
So one thing to know about copyright
is that it lasts 75 years, and then the copyright expires.
And whatever that content gets released into the public domain,
and this is now--
everyone can use it freely.
So a lot of people who have lived in the past,
all their great works are in the public domain,
which is great for everyone.
So the rationale here is that you're incentivizing innovation.
So when an artist or a creator creates something,
you want to protect their--
you don't want someone else to just take it,
so you protect them for a while.
But after 75 years, presumably, it's not worth protecting,
or they're passed away, or something.
So it doesn't make sense to keep things copyright anymore.
So basically, everything on the internet is copyrighted.
So you're saying, wait a minute.
So that means is everything-- if I train on anything,
that's a copyright violation?
Well, not necessarily.
So everything is copyrighted, but you
can use copyrighted works.
And the way you do it is A, you either get a license for it,
or B, you appeal to the fair use clause.
So a license from contract law is something
that a licensor grants to a licensee.
It basically says, don't sue me.
You can use this work in the ways that the license permits.
So there's a really nice license called Creative Commons,
which allows something to act like it
was in the public domain.
It enables free distribution of copyrighted work.
So examples include Wikipedia, Open CourseWare, Khan Academy,
all these things.
It was created in 2001 to essentially bridge
public domain and existing copyright,
because otherwise you have to wait 75 years.
But what if the creator says, I actually want people to use it.
They can now have a means, a legal means of saying,
I put a Creative Commons license on it.
It's going to act like it's in the public domain,
and everyone can use it.
So, so far, things in the public domain
and things that have Creative Commons licenses are permissive.
You can use it.
But there are many other times where
you don't have-- it's not a Creative Commons license,
it's not in the public domain, you have to get a license.
So if you have money, you can pay someone
to give you a license.
So there's a bunch of deals between model developers
and content, I guess, platforms, that
allow the model developers to license the data for training
foundation models.
OK, so that's the first thing.
You can get a license-- either Creative Commons,
or you can pay someone for a license.
Now if you don't want to pay, you
can appeal to fair use, which is a more complicated matter.
So this is section 107 of the Copyright Act.
And there are-- basically fair use says, I can use this anyway,
even if I don't have a license, and these four factors determine
whether fair use applies.
So the first one is the purpose or character of the use.
What are you trying to do with it?
And none of these are hard rules.
They're just tendencies which have
to be weighed in court if it comes to that.
So, for example, if you're trying to do something
for education, it is more likely to be
fair use than if you're trying to sell and make
money off of it.
If you're trying to-- if you transform something,
then that's going to be more favored
than if you just literally host the identical copy.
The nature of the actual copyrighted work
is also important.
So things that are more factual are
more likely to be fair use than fictional works.
Because if you write a summary of World War--
a page about facts about World War II,
there's less protection over my really creative poem.
And then the amount of portion of the original work.
So using a snippet is favored over the whole work.
So if you just take a little bit,
that's not as bad as taking everything.
So that's fairly straightforward.
And the final thing is related to original motivation.
It was like, why are you--
why copyright at all is to protect and align
the economic incentives.
So the effect that what the use has
on the market for the original work.
So if you take an author's work and you provide an alternative,
and that decreases the amount that the original author could
monetize their work, that is seen as potentially bad.
But if you're transforming it in a way and going to a new market,
or doing something else with it, then that's
going to be treated more favorably.
So here are some examples of fair use.
You can watch a movie and write a summary of it.
You can re-implement an idea, like an algorithm--
not copy the code.
And then there was this famous lawsuit between Authors Guild
and Google.
So if you go to Google Books, you
can see snippets of various books which are copyrighted.
So there was a huge deal about whether this
was deemed fair use, because you are redistributing
other copyrighted work, and eventually--
eventually meaning after 11 years--
this lawsuit was settled in favor of Google,
which is why this thing exists.
And this has set some precedent for thinking about
whether language model training is fair use.
One thing to note is that copyright is not
about verbatim memorization.
So this might be, I think, for an ML audience,
this might be a little bit new because a lot of papers
are focused on verbatim memorization.
That's one way you can violate copyright, but not the only one.
So for example, plots and characters can be copyrightable.
So you can copyright Harry Potter
the character, not any particular book, or anything.
But there are some exceptions.
For example, if you're parodying something--
and so you're creating something that looks like a derivative,
but as long as you're making fun of it,
it's actually more likely to be fair use.
So, yeah.
So a lot of copyright is about semantics.
It's definitely not about N-gram overlap,
and also about the economics.
So what is the implication for language models?
So first off, copying data.
Even if you're not training, even the mere fact of copying--
which is in the word copyright--
is potentially a violation already,
even if you don't do anything with it.
Training a model--
I guess this is not really a-- let's see, how do I take that?
This is not necessarily a fact, but intuitively
has a transformative flavor.
Because it's certainly not--
it certainly seems different than just
rehosting another work.
It's doing something transformative.
And in some sense, the models are really
trained on this data as a means to an end.
You are trying to extract the general idea,
learn about the world and how it works,
rather than only just the concrete expression.
And the other thing is that regardless of copyright,
language models can definitely affect the market.
So I think this is also-- remember, that's
the fourth item for fair use.
So by negatively affecting the market,
you are more likely to be ruled not fair use.
So fair use is a little bit slippery.
Suppose you have fair use, or you have a license.
Remember that there's still terms of service that allow
or prevent you from actually just getting a piece of work.
For example, YouTube has all these videos which are licensed,
but the terms of service prohibits
just downloading the videos using a bot, like scraping,
which is another layer.
So there's multiple layers of restrictions here.
So let me talk a little bit about where things
are on the legal landscape.
So back in 2023, New York Times filed suit against OpenAI,
saying you train on our news articles, and look,
here's evidence.
We were able to actually prompt ChatGPT to generate a news
article almost verbatim.
I don't think this is still pending.
There's a case against Anthropic where the allegation was
you pirated millions of books, and you trained on these books
to make Claude.
Just last year, this was a landmark ruling
that said, actually, this particular instance of training
is fair use.
However, Anthropic, you're still in trouble
because you pirated all these books, and that is a no-no.
So notice that this has nothing to do with training, just
the mere fact of pirating--
I mean, which is not a new thing--
is illegal.
Anthropic actually, interestingly,
had bought and scanned all the books,
which is actually fair use.
The Court said you're allowed to scan.
You buy a bunch of books, rip off the bindings,
scan it, and digitize it for your own use.
That's fair use.
But that doesn't absolve you of your sin of pirating.
So you can't pirate and then buy it and say, actually, never
mind what I just did first.
So the outcome is that Anthropic paid 1.5 billion
to settle the authors.
So this is about $3,000 a book.
So there's also a lawsuit against Meta.
The allegation was that you trained on our books--
sorry-- and this was, as we'll see later,
actually revealed in the Llama paper.
And the judgment which came right after Anthropic was, yes,
training is fair use.
And then they also torrented some books,
so that's still pending.
So that's probably-- if precedent holds,
this is also not going to be good for Meta.
So the summary so far is training, so to speak,
has been deemed of fair use, or at least
has been not deemed not fair use.
The rulings have so far been narrow.
It's not to say that any training on any copyrighted
content is fair use, but in these cases, it's fine.
Pirating books is clearly illegal.
I guess we already knew that.
But this is still a very active and evolving area.
Any questions about the sources of data?
I think, before we get into the actual datasets,
I just want to set the stage with this more
general social context.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah?
The question is, what do I think of voice data and ElevenLabs?
I don't know too much about that, so we can talk offline.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah?
--because I guess if I own some asset, it's reasonable for me
to be like [INAUDIBLE].
Am I allowed to-- usually it's Creative Commons,
but can I update my license later on to block certain usage?
And so, what is the role of time playing
in this, like I then train on the older version with more
a more permissive license if the creator copied it
to a more restrictive?
Yeah, so the question is, what happens with time?
If you have one license and then it gets changed, what happens?
So first, I'm not a lawyer.
But second, so this--
so the first license I believe you're still
allowed to train on it.
But what happens is that the license usually
applies to not just, let's say, a fixed set of documents--
for example, Reddit.
There's constantly new content being created,
and the license being changed means
that you wouldn't be able to train on the later things.
OK, so let's look at various sources of data.
So let's go back to crawling.
So most model developers have their own crawler,
because they want to have full control over what the data is.
Fortunately for the rest of us, if you
don't want to build your own crawler,
there's something called Common Crawl, which has been around
for quite some time since 2007.
And every month they run a web crawl, gets about three
to five billion web pages.
Each crawl has some overlap with the previous crawl,
but they try to diversify and get new pages.
So there's 300 billion pages so far, which seems--
this was from their website.
It seems a little bit big, because if you
multiply this number by 20, you don't quite get 300 billion.
But that's what they say.
So how many URLs are out there?
That's really hard to estimate.
So the Google search index is at least 100 petabytes,
according to them.
And, each Common Crawl dump has about 2 billion web pages.
So that's about 372tb.
And this is not including images,
this is just mostly focused on the text.
So crawling is conceptually straightforward,
but all the gory details are in the implementation.
You start with a bunch of URLs, and then you iterate.
It's basically graph traversal.
You pop a URL from a queue, you download it,
and then you look at all the hyperlinks in that page,
and then you add them to the queue.
And generally this is done in parallel over many machines.
And there's many decisions here--
which pages to download, you have to respect robots.txt,
don't overload the server.
Sometimes the websites change, and so you
want a policy that will download frequently changed pages,
but not spend time downloading pages that don't change.
So there's some policy around that.
And I mentioned before, URLs are dynamic,
so sometimes the same URL leads to different content
depending on some state of the browser.
But also, many URLs might lead to the same content,
so there's a lot of duplication that
happens if you're not careful.
In particular, mirror sites explicitly is about duplication.
So Common Crawl releases their dumps in two formats.
One is a WARC file.
So this is the raw HTTP response.
So remember, HTTP protocol is that you
send a get, here's a URL, and then out comes a HTTP response,
and the WARC file is that response.
They also do some processing.
They convert to a WET file, which is necessarily
a loss-y process.
It turns out that this is not necessarily the best way
to use the web.
The HTML to text, there's many tools
for this, including trafilatura and resiliparse,
and the way you convert actually does matter.
So this is from the DataComp LLM paper, which
we'll talk a little bit about.
Data is an ablation, where you look at the web files
that Common Crawl releases versus these other tools,
and it seems like trafilatura and resiliparse are better.
So one thing you can do is just rely on general web crawls.
But often, the web is not a uniform place.
It's not like there's a bunch of websites,
and you just get some random fraction of them,
and that's your dataset.
There are specific pockets of really interesting, high quality
content, and I'll talk about three of those--
Wikipedia, GitHub, and arXiv.
So Wikipedia, all of you know about.
It's been around since 2001, and now there's
67 million articles around all these different languages.
And Wikipedia is not all content by any means.
You can't have original thought in it,
because everything has to be referenced and cited.
So in some sense you could argue that Wikipedia
doesn't contain anything that's not already on the web.
Well actually, that's not true, because they can also
cite books, which are-- obviously you can't easily get
them, so, Wikipedia is so good.
And also, there's articles based on notability,
so not everyone can get a Wikipedia article about them.
So anyone on the internet can write this content.
This was the radical thing about wikis, and it's still a miracle,
I think, to me that this actually works.
It just happens that any vandalism
gets reverted by administrators, or bots, I guess, these days.
There's a small number of Wikipedians-- as any peer
production system, there's a small set
of people who do most of the work.
And for example, this guy has 5 million edits.
And one thing about Wikipedia is that every few weeks,
they do a periodic dump.
So basically they take all of Wikipedia
packaged into a nice TAR file, and then you
can just download that.
So this is important because you don't need to crawl Wikipedia.
In fact, they don't want you to crawl Wikipedia.
They just want you to download this if you're going to crawl,
and this is much better than crawling.
Just a fun aside, or good to know,
is that there's this paper that says you can actually
poison Wikipedia.
So you might think that this vandalism gets reverted.
So if you do-- attacker tries to do something fishy,
you'll just get it rolled back.
But what Carlini realized is that these periodic dumps
happen at a regular cadence.
And so, what you can do is you can go in
and you can just edit it right before the dump happens.
And then the dump happens, and then the edits get rolled back,
but the dump still has the malicious content.
If you're able to inject things into web pages,
that means you can cause--
there's works that show that you can cause the model to, let's
say, ascribe negative sentiment to any trigger phrase,
like the iPhone.
So one takeaway here is that if you consider adversaries,
even so-called high quality contents might
contain bad things in them.
I think this has been fixed since then.
OK, so GitHub is a good place for code,
and code is important not just for
if you want coding capabilities for your language model,
but if you want general reasoning.
So GitHub all of you know.
Again, it's a live service for hosting code repositories.
Been around since 2008, about the same age as Common Crawl.
It has 420 million repositories, 28 million are public.
Each repository contains-- it's not a file, as you know,
it's a directory with commit history, issues, pull requests,
and comments.
Code has generally a lot of duplicates,
and it's just because either copying code, or forking code.
And GitHub has deemed it-- you're
allowed to train on any public repository
with a permissive license.
So MIT or Apache licenses are fine.
So remember, there's two types of data
when you talk about GitHub.
There's the repository data, which
you can just go and download through the GitHub Git protocol.
And again, you shouldn't scrape GitHub,
you should just download the repository.
And then the metadata associated with each repository-- issues
and pull requests, and so on.
These are made actually via the GitHub Archive, which gives you
hourly snapshots of this event stream, which I think
is really interesting data.
It's basically every single comment, or star, or action
on GitHub that gets recorded.
There's this software heritage foundation
that is focused on the repository, not the metadata,
and they aggregate GitHub.
GitHub is not the only place where code shows up.
There's also smaller entities like GitLab, Bitbucket,
and so on.
And they aggregate all that, those repositories
So arXiv, just very briefly-- everyone knows arXiv.
This has been around as a site that allows people
to share papers since 1991.
Started with physics, and now has a lot of other areas in it.
Each of the three million submissions
has the metadata, a PDF, and optional LaTeX source.
So already you should be thinking, well,
what does it mean to train on arXiv?
It's not clear, because this is, well,
you have to convert the PDF into text,
or you can use the LaTeX source, which is a bunch of files.
It's not peer-reviewed, but there is some approval process,
and authors can choose to maintain the rights,
or put in the Creative Commons, which--
so everything is actually very clearly licensed.
All the metadata is under permissive license
so you can use that regardless, and then you can go
and you look at all the papers that
are Creative Commons license.
You download those, and you can use them.
And I think most arXiv papers are Creative Commons.
And then again, this is available.
You don't crawl arXiv, you just go down to bulk
download it from some website.
So any questions about sources of data?
Yeah?
Are there any restrictions on usage of data,
which is generated by models?
Are there restrictions on data?
Generated by models.
Yeah.
I mean, [? synthetic ?] [? data ?] models.
Oh, I see.
We'll talk about that a little bit later.
So the question is, what about model-generated,
like synthetic data?
Are you allowed to use it?
The short answer is probably yes.
Yeah?
When using crawlers like [INAUDIBLE] Crawl
and stuff like that, I guess-- because you mentioned earlier
that there are websites that have
a lot of pirated books on it.
How do you ensure that those types of websites
don't show up in your crawl?
Yeah.
So the question is, there's a lot
of websites with pirated books.
So if you're just doing a web crawl,
you can't look at all the websites.
So how do you make sure that everything is kosher?
And that's part of the difficulty is, you can't.
And so, there's-- most likely in Common Crawl,
there are copyrighted books and content that you are not
supposed to train on, and you can--
will appeal to fair use.
Remember, everything is copyright.
Books are not remarkably different from your website,
for example. both are copyrighted.
Probably, a book author has more of a--
if they want to go into court, they'll
probably be able to protect that better because it's published
than your website, but still.
And I'll talk a little bit about later.
If you really, really want to be careful,
you cam do something I'll show later.
So what I'm going to do now is to now talk
about the various datasets that are actually
used in building models, starting all the way back
to 2019.
So we've talked about the origin of data and source of data,
so you have a feeling for just the general data landscape.
And so, let's start with BERT.
So BERT was from 2018, and they trained-- back in the day,
they just trained on Wikipedia and books.
So what is this books?
So there's this website called Smashwords.
It was created that allow anyone to just put an ebook up
to publish, and they had about half a million books in 2024.
So in 2015, there was this paper who just scraped Smashwords--
sorry, took the books that were free, and just made a corpus.
This was back in the innocent days
when no one was paying attention to any of this.
So this books corpus was around for many years
in the academic community.
Since then, it has been taken down
because it violated the terms of service.
Just because it was free and you can get it, doesn't mean it
was legally allowed.
So one thing to note about Bert is
that the sequences were documents rather than sentences.
All the language modeling research
before that was focused on sentences.
So in 2019, GPT-2 came around.
And so what did they do?
So they wanted to get high quality web content.
And at that time, people knew about Common Crawl,
but somehow the Common Crawl data was too messy.
So what they did was came up with this clever idea
where you can take--
you look at pages that are outgoing links from Reddit posts
with greater than three karma.
So a good post must link to good websites.
So you grab those pages, and you get a 40 gigabytes
of text, 8 million pages.
They never released this data, but there
was an open replication of webtext,
which people used quite a bit.
So that's GPT-2.
So as you're going through this, I guess think about both--
there's many methods of filtering and collecting data,
and it's interesting to look at these design choices, and.
So CCNET was developed by, at that time, Facebook.
So the goal was to create large high quality data
sets for pre-training.
And they were especially interested
in low resource languages.
So they didn't want some very manual process
that only worked for English.
So they did a bunch of things.
They did deduplication, and language identification
to train a classifier to detect a language,
and keep only the language that you're looking for.
And for quality filtering, the idea that they had was
they wanted to keep documents that look like Wikipedia.
So Wikipedia at the time was deemed good, high quality
content, and they used a language model that
was trained on Wikipedia, and you
score a probability of a new document under that language
model to gauge how Wikipedia-like it was.
So rather than outgoing links to Reddit,
they use a language model on Wikipedia.
And they show that because you can get much more data,
you can actually outperform just training on Wikipedia.
And this was a tool that will later
appear in some other papers.
So here is another work.
This is from Google in 2019.
So this is called C4.
So this paper as actually more famous for the T5 model,
which pushes the idea that you should just
treat all the NLP tasks in a world as text-to-text.
But actually, a big contribution of this paper,
which is a very long report, was the C4 dataset.
And the observation, which was very clear at that time, which
is that Common Crawl is mostly not useful for natural language.
There was this idea that you have these small datasets,
and they were high quality, or you had
Common Crawl, which was a mess.
And any attempt to train on Common Crawl just led
to junk results.
So people were thinking like, how
do I get a larger but high quality subset of Common Crawl?
So we saw the Reddit idea, we saw the Wikipedia-like language
model idea.
C4 used a different idea, and this
is saying, let's just define a bunch of rules, which turned out
to be fairly effective.
So basically, they keep lines that
end in punctuation, that have more than five words,
remove pages with fewer than three sentences,
remove pages that contain any bad words.
Remove things like terms of use, boilerplate.
Interestingly, remove the curly brace,
which filters out a lot of code-- so clearly at that time,
they weren't thinking about code models--
and they filtered out anything that was not English.
The end result is that you have 156 billion tokens,
so 800 gigabytes of text.
So this is much larger than the GPT-2 dataset, which
was only 40 gigabytes of text.
A bit later there was some analysis done in C4
which showed--
here's the websites that were represented.
So you have a bunch of Wikipedia,
patents was a very common thing.
They also released a WebText-like document.
They also use this idea of links in Reddit posts--
from Reddit posts with greater than three karma,
and filtered to those pages.
So they were able to get, using this method,
17gb of text using 12 Common Crawl dumps.
Remember, webtext was 40 gigabytes,
which means that Common Crawl is maybe incomplete, or doesn't
have everything, because if it had everything,
you should be able to hit 40.
And they showed that at that time,
you could use this data to improve
on a bunch of NLP benchmarks.
So we've seen using rules, things
that look like Wikipedia, Reddit links, and now let's
talk about GPT-3.
So GPT-3, the dataset was--
they used Common Crawl, they did their own processing.
There is this WebText, which was essentially the GPT-2 dataset,
but expanded.
Notice that there's some overlap.
Common Crawl does overlap with this,
but this is, in some sense, a more targeted distribution.
There is this-- in the paper, it's
described as Books1 and Books2, which is internet-based books
corpora, so this remains a mystery exactly what it is,
and Wikipedia.
So the result was about 500 gigabytes
of text, 400 billion tokens.
And to do the Common Crawl processing,
they trained a quality classifier to distinguish things
they deemed to be high quality from the rest,
and they did some fuzzy deduplication
because WebText and Common Crawl had dupes.
So this paper followed the idea of using a classifier
to do quality classification.
So after GPT-3 came out, this was, I think, a big event.
And there were a number of efforts
to try to do things in the open.
So one of the initial efforts was
The Pile, which is a grassroots effort from EleutherAI, where
they had a bunch of people in this Discord just jamming
and figuring out high quality sources.
And they came up with this list in the end.
And today, this is still pretty interesting and diverse.
It has Common Crawl, it has PubMed.
This has this thing called Books3, which we'll talk about.
ArXiv, GitHub, which we talked about.
Wikipedia, IRC, another BooksCorpus, Philosophy Papers,
and so on.
They included this Enron Emails dataset.
So Enron went bust in 2002 and all the emails were released,
and this is one of the few email datasets we have,
which is a weird distribution, I think, for email.
But that's what you get.
So Project Gutenberg was--
so let's talk about books a little bit.
So project Gutenberg was started in 1971,
and it only includes books that received copyright clearance.
So mostly books in the public domain.
There's this packaging of Gutenberg into PG-19,
which is Gutenberg before 2019.
Which is, I guess most of them, because for them
to be in public domain, you have to wait 75 years.
So Books3, which is this interesting dataset that
appeared in The Pile.
So this is described actually as 200k books from a shadow library
called Bibliotik that concludes all books from your favorite
authors.
And at that time-- again, 2020, no one was paying attention.
People used it to train models, and since then, it
has been taken down.
So you cannot use, or should not use Books3 anymore.
We'll come back to Books3 again.
So Stack Exchange you've probably used quite a bit,
although I guess these days maybe less so because of AI.
There's a bunch of user-contributed questions
and answers, started in 2008.
And one thing that is interesting about this dataset
is that it's a Q&A format, and this is quite
close to a real application.
So normally, you think about pre-training data as here's
Wikipedia articles, just like raw text.
But some parts of the web are actually--
look supervised, like what you would want
to ask your language model.
Which I think, maybe, helps the model
learn certain types of question answering behaviors.
So not everything is super magically emergent.
It's like, well, this type of data does exist on the web.
So there's also-- this data has metadata,
which is like the number of votes
which are useful for filtering.
And again, this data is released in data dumps
that allows you to just download without crawling it.
So now we're in 2021.
There was another paper from DeepMind.
They trained a model called Gopher,
which was never released, and actually
was subsumed by Chinchilla.
But the description of the data, I think,
is actually really good.
You should read this paper, because I
think it's very thorough in the way
that they describe the data processing.
Well, except for the parts where they don't tell you
what's in the data.
So they created this massive web,
and they had C4, which remember, was the dataset
that we looked at before from Google.
They train on books, news, GitHub, and Wikipedia.
They don't say anything about how they got that.
So for the MassiveWeb, they kept English, deduped,
and their quality filtering was also based on manual rules.
And part of the reason for this is that they
had more control over that.
So I think, as you can see, there
is this division between people who wanted to use rules,
and people who wanted to use classifiers.
So they got, as the name suggests,
a massive amount of text, but their model
was only trained on a very small fraction of this dataset.
So in 2022 Llama 1 came out, and the dataset here-- this
was actually a very nice paper in that it detailed their data
processing.
So this is probably one of the last non-open,
fully open models that actually talk about their data
processing.
So they have Common Crawl processed with CCNET,
which you know about.
The classification, though, was whether the page
was a reference of Wikipedia, not whether it is actually
a Wikipedia article.
So the idea is that well, maybe Wikipedia articles
are too stylized.
And we know that Wikipedia articles references
a bunch of other articles which are presumably good,
so let's call those the good websites.
They had C4, they did a bunch of processing
on GitHub to keep permissive licenses, Wikipedia.
They trained on Books3 and project Gutenberg.
So Books3 really got them in a lot of trouble
because they're just announcing to the world that
hey, I trained on this dataset.
And if you look back, oh, this came
from-- where did it come from?
It came from The Pile.
Oh, it came from a shadow library.
So that's why people don't want to talk about their data
anymore.
So they looked at arXiv, and actually used
the LaTeX to do the processing, Stack Exchange,
and they got 1.2 trillion tokens.
They didn't actually release this dataset,
but they had enough of a description in their processing
that this was reproduced by Together's RedPajama V1
dataset, which was then used in other sources.
So as you can see here, RedPajama V1
initially also contained Books3, which has now been stripped out.
So various decisions made early on about copyright actually
influence-- have a fairly big watershed.
So let's talk about RefinedWeb.
So this is a paper that tried to make a point that web data is
all you need.
So the web, in some sense, is everything.
And then we talked about all these specialized
sources, like there's GitHub and arXiv, and Stack Exchange.
And they said, well, what happens
if we just stick with the web?
So they did a good job of doing the transformation from HTML
to text.
They filtered using the Gopher rules, which is basically keep
things that look like English.
They explicitly, at that time, still
said avoid ML-based filtering to avoid biases.
I don't want to find an overly narrow subset of the web.
They did some deduplication, and they had five trillion tokens.
They released about 600 billion of them.
So FineWeb from Hugging Face was a replication of RefinedWeb,
but improved it.
So they took all the Common Crawl dumps at that time,
did some filtering--
again, using manual rules to not inject biases--
deduped, did PII removal, and got 15 trillion tokens.
So you can see that the size of these datasets
is growing quite a bit.
So then there is this Dolma dataset from AI2,
and this is a dataset that includes their own processing
of Common Crawl, The Stack, which we'll talk about,
before C4, which you know about, and a bunch of other things.
And the Reddit dataset was from this project called PushShift.
And at that time, you could still get this data,
and you can train on it before things got locked down.
AI2 has their own crawl of academic papers called
Semantic Scholar, so they derived a dataset based on that.
So let's look at their Common Crawl processing.
So they use language identification.
So this was model-based, but quality filtering still
avoid model-based filtering.
And then they removed toxicity using rules and a classifier.
And they got three trillion tokens out of that.
So DCLM, I think, was maybe a point
where this idea of model-based quality filtering
started to really become the norm here.
So DataComp, the initial motivation
was to define some sort of pipeline
so that people can try different data methods in a standard way,
and show results.
But I think the main way that I think
people use this is just using their dataset that they released
to train models and do other things.
So they processed Common Crawl to produce DCLM-pool.
So this is completely unfiltered.
And if you look at this dataset, this is massive.
240 trillion tokens.
This is probably more than the number of tokens
that anyone really trains on.
But a lot of this is fairly low quality,
so then they had a pipeline where all that gets filtered.
If you only keep English, you have
some of rules to really narrow it down.
You do dedupe, and then you do this model-based filtering,
and you end up with something that's 1.4%.
And this is the data set that we'll see actually works
pretty well.
So the model-based filtering-- and this was strangely good.
So to train a classifier, they took OpenHermes,
which is essentially instruction data that
was generated by GPT-4, and ELI5,
which is a subreddit with various questions and answers.
So this is-- let's see.
These are the type of questions that are in ELI5.
So anyway, you get the idea.
So it's kind of weird, but somehow this works.
So the negative examples are anything from RefinedWeb, which
is, remember, it's just a very loosely filtered version
of the web.
It's basically the web, and it got 3.8 trillion tokens.
They train a fastText classifier-- think about it just
as a linear classifier.
And then they show that this magical classifier, quality
classifier, outperforms a bunch of other things that they tried.
So, DCLM.
This became, for a while, at least in the open community,
a bit of a gold standard for quality filtering.
Let's move on to Nemotron.
So Nemotron-- this is from NVIDIA--
they said that well, DCLM filters too aggressively.
It's removing most of the data.
And remember, they only got--
how many-- 3.8 trillion tokens.
So we need more tokens.
So what do we do?
We are going to do something more, I guess, elaborate.
We're going to prompt our existing
model to score FineWeb documents based on educational value.
So we're going to prompt a language model and say,
is this educational or not?
Go add a bunch of labels, train a fastText model.
So that's one classifier.
Another classifier is just using the DCLM classifier.
So we're going to use those classifiers.
We're also going to use synthetic data.
So this is probably one of the--
I don't know if-- it's probably not the first,
but, one of the main datasets that really
lean into synthetic data for pre-training.
So they had, for low quality data,
as deemed by these classifiers, you
use a language model to rephrase it to make it more--
look like Wikipedia.
For high quality data, we use a language model
to generate various tasks.
For example, given a Wikipedia article,
I can generate question answers, or I
can generate like, please summarize this document,
extract key information from it, and so on.
So they resulted in a dataset that was 6 trillion tokens.
So this is substantially larger than DCLM.
And just for reference, this is still kind of
small by some consideration.
So Llama 3 was trained on 15 trillion tokens,
Qwen3 was trained on 36 trillion.
Although there is this--
it's not clear how big these unique tokens are,
because when you look at [INAUDIBLE] counts in language
modeling papers, some of it is repeated.
Like if you do two epochs, that's
twice the number of tokens, so you have to be careful
when you look at those numbers.
And they show that the dataset is better.
Their high quality subset beats the previous datasets
So up until now, we've seen a bunch of different methods
for filtering.
I think all of these look very similar at some level.
You take a web crawl, you either decide
I'm going to use rules to filter,
or I'm going to use a model.
If I'm going to use a model, then I
have to decide what looks like good data,
and then try to train a classifier,
and classify all my documents, and select.
And there seems to be a trade-off
between you can take a lot of Common Crawl--
you can get 240 trillion tokens if you want,
but that's probably going to be really low quality.
Or you can get one trillion tokens,
and there's some sweet spot in-between.
Let me talk about two final things.
So code, and going back to this question of licensing.
So The Stack is a very nice project
that was trying to make a really good coding data set, since it
was clear by 2022 that coding was
going to be really important.
So what they did in the initial version
is that they clone 137 repos.
They kept the ones that were permissively licensed,
remove near-duplicates, and resulted in one-- sorry,
three terabytes of code.
And then in 2024, they had an update.
And here they took more the metadata,
like the issues, comments, and PRs from GitHub,
the repositories from the Software Heritage,
which we talked about.
They also scraped documentation from various websites
by crawling them.
They did a bunch of processing.
So in GitHub repos, you have binary files which you probably
don't want to train on.
They have malware, you get rid of that.
A lot of GitHub, especially these PRs, are bots,
so you have to filter that.
Dedupe, do PII redaction.
There's a lot pull requests and stuff,
and they basically subsample to keep it representative
and the dataset manageable.
They also did this thing, which was I thought was nice,
which is that there's many programming languages out there.
There's a lot of Python, a lot of C,
but low resource languages like Nim-- which I hadn't even heard
of-- they're not that common.
So what they do is they compile this code
into a low-level intermediate language,
LLVM, which everything, like C Compiler, can compile into this,
and they have juxtaposed the low resource
language and the intermediate representation.
So then the language model can actually
learn the mapping between the shared low level representation,
which has a lot of data on, and the thing that it does
has less data on.
And just for fun, you add in all the other good stuff
that you can.
So Stack V2 is mostly code, and then
plus other things that were used to train their coding models.
And one thing about pull requests
is that pull requests and all the metadata is not,
by its nature, a linearized sequence.
So there has to be some steps taken to linearize it.
So one important thing you have to decide
is how much context to provide.
So for example, an event might just be,
I change one line of code.
And that could just be one line, but presumably
to learn that, you want to provide some context, maybe
a few lines around it, or maybe the entire file surrounding
that diff.
And these are some design decisions
that you have to make for linearization.
And so at the end of the day, the tokens that they train on
look something like this, where it's
this XML-like structured data, where you have the PR,
and then you have a bunch of diffs.
And then for comments, you have basically the events
of a comment was posted, what the review state of that PR was
and so on and so forth.
So it's not just learning how to generate
code, but also the software development process around code.
So finally, I'll talk about the common pile.
So recall that almost all the data on the internet
is copyrighted.
Some of it is permissively licensed, some of it
is even in the public domain.
And while you can appeal to fair use and say,
I'm going to train on it anyway, this is not quite settled.
So if you're very, very risk-averse,
then you say, well, if I don't know whether it is OK,
that's a no.
If you take that attitude, then that's what common pile did.
So can you train a good model with only permissively licensed
data?
Or rather, how far can you get?
So this was a project that went and scoured the internet
for all the different types of data
that they could possibly find that was worth training on,
that was permissively licensed.
It includes Stack V2 in code.
It turns out that a lot of government proceedings
are actually permissively licensed,
wikis, some things on the web-- some new sites are actually
permissively licensed, academic papers, online forums,
things that are in the public domain, educational resources,
and so on.
So in the end, there were 8 terabytes
of data, which is actually pretty
good for permissively licensed data.
Doing this project is actually much harder
than maybe it sounds at first glance.
It's not just as simple oh, you look at the license
and it's like, oh yep, Apache, or CC, good.
There's some subtleties, versus license laundering.
So people are sloppy with licenses.
So people might take some copyright work
and just slap a CC BY on it.
Anyone can write this on the internet,
and it's hard to tell whether this is real or not.
There's also this common practice where, for example,
Dolma is permissively licensed.
Remember, Dolma is the AI2 collection.
But collection licenses don't extend to the individual works.
So the collection is--
I mean, first of all, there's a question
of whether collections--
I think collections can be copyrighted,
but I guess you can put a license on anything.
But the individual works are not necessarily good.
So you can't just look at data sets on Hugging Face,
and you-- many data sets on Hugging Face you see,
they have a permissive license.
But if you dig deeper, it's actually
not permissively licensed at the individual level.
And they also made a decision to forego training
on any synthetic data, because training language models
on unlicensed data is unclear.
So probably it's fine because technically, these
are open weight models with MIT license.
You can do whatever.
You can use them however you want,
but these language models were presumably also trained
on unlicensed data.
So it's a little bit of data laundering
if you are really honest here.
So with this data, they compare it
with a bunch of other models like the first Llama, MPT,
and Qwen.
And on a bunch of benchmarks, they show that this is not bad.
I would say it's not as good as the Qwen models for sure,
but it's certainly outperforming the very old--
this is from 2023, I guess.
So quite old models.
So I would say, the conclusion here
is that you can do reasonably, but I
think it's still pretty tough to compete
without doing more tokens.
But I don't think this is the final word on it,
and I think you can probably eke more out of publicly
permissive licenses if you try.
OK, so to summarize this lecture here.
So maybe hopefully now I've given you some appreciation
that data is a very rich topic.
It's not that data just falls from the sky,
or you just go on Hugging Face and you download a dataset.
Data has to come from somewhere.
And there's also a technical but also social context
in which data comes, because at the top,
the internet is a bunch of live services.
Someone has to do the work of producing raw data,
whether it be the website that gives you dumps,
or someone has to build a crawler, or something.
And then, someone has to make the decision of how to process
it into usable form--
filtering, transformation, deduplication, all these things
have an impact on the quality of your final language model.
And notice that filtering is probably one
of the most important things.
How do you go from 200 trillion tokens
to less than three trillion tokens?
I think that obviously is a huge reduction, which I think
merits a lot of attention.
Data is, in some sense, a key ingredient that
differentiates language models.
A lot of language models are roughly the same kind
of transformer architecture, but data is depending
on how you process it.
It can make a pretty big difference.
There's plenty of legal and ethical issues
around data, more than I can get into this lecture.
And also, this process is very messy.
Unlike some of the other parts of this class where things
are maybe more based on first principles,
data processing is, right now at least, a lot just
based on vibes you set up.
You define this classifier, you define this rule,
you set some threshold.
So there are many opportunities to improve.
So as you do your assignment four,
maybe think about whether there's better ways to do this,
and this could be maybe a research direction.
OK, so that's it for today.
So next time I'll continue talking about data.
I'll talk a bit about post-training data,
and a bit more about filtering.